<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-07T22:34:04-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mileena Rayne</title><subtitle>Dark fantasy author and musician creating raw, honest stories about trauma, faith, and human resilience. Read Blood of the Wild Gods series and listen to original songs about mental health.</subtitle><author><name>Mileena Rayne</name></author><entry><title type="html">From Silence to Science: A Survivor’s Journey from Religious Abuse to Royal Commission Testimony</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/07/05/from-silence-to-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Silence to Science: A Survivor’s Journey from Religious Abuse to Royal Commission Testimony" /><published>2025-07-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-07-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/07/05/from-silence-to-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/07/05/from-silence-to-science/"><![CDATA[<div class="content-warning-box">
<strong>Content Warning:</strong> This post contains detailed descriptions of childhood sexual abuse, grooming, religious trauma, and systematic institutional failure. Please read with care for yourself.
</div>

<hr />

<p>Sometimes the most powerful response to systematic abuse is to study the very mechanisms that enabled it.</p>

<p>When someone reaches out to share their story with me, I can usually sense the weight they carry before I even begin reading. But this particular account arrived with something I don’t often encounter: the measured precision of someone who has not only survived their trauma, but dissected it with scientific rigor. Someone who transformed their pain into a doctoral-level understanding of exactly how cults destroy lives—and more importantly, how survivors can reclaim them.</p>

<p>This person didn’t just escape the Jehovah’s Witness organization. They studied it. Testified against it before the Australian Royal Commission. Earned degrees in psychology and counseling. Researched the very coercive control tactics that were used against them. They turned their lived experience into a roadmap for understanding high-control groups, becoming both survivor and scholar in service of others still trapped in similar nightmares.</p>

<p>Their story spans decades: from a sick, anxious child trying desperately to be righteous enough to deserve love, to a confident researcher who can name every manipulation tactic the Governing Body employs. It’s a journey from silence to voice, from victim to advocate, from broken faith to hard-won wisdom.</p>

<p>This is their story, shared with permission and told with the honor it deserves.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-weight-of-righteousness">The Weight of Righteousness</h2>

<p>In 2012, when then-Prime Minister Julia Gillard announced the establishment of the Royal Commission into Institutional Responses to Child Sexual Abuse, this person was living what appeared to be the model Jehovah’s Witness life. Married with two teenage daughters. Helping run a family plumbing business. Maintaining the exhausting schedule that every devoted Witness knows by heart: daily Bible study, three meetings per week, constant preaching about God’s Kingdom and the approaching Armageddon.</p>

<p>But beneath this veneer of spiritual prosperity, their body was telling a different story:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I was dealing with anxiety, depression and bouts of panic attacks, alongside regular throat/chest infections.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>They consulted doctors for the physical symptoms and psychiatrists for the mental illness, but still believed the Watchtower’s promise that true healing came from Jehovah through prayer, Bible study, and approaching the Elders for guidance. When the Elders inevitably prescribed more prayer, more meetings, more service (essentially telling them to “throw myself on Jehovah”), it only added to their stress and deepened their sense of unworthiness.</p>

<p>What they didn’t understand then was that their body was carrying the weight of childhood trauma they had spent decades trying to forget. The announcement of the Royal Commission would change everything, triggering PTSD and unleashing a flood of intrusive memories and nightmares about an Elder from their childhood in Narrogin, Western Australia.</p>

<p>Memories of what had been done to them. And memories of how the organization had silenced them when they finally found the courage to speak.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-art-of-grooming">The Art of Grooming</h2>

<p>The abuse began when they were around twelve years old, introduced to an Elder’s family through his daughter at a Jehovah’s Witness gathering. What seemed like innocent friendship was actually the beginning of a carefully orchestrated grooming process that would span years.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“She seemed to want to be friends with me and I think our mothers arranged for us to stay at each other’s house. The first time I stayed at their house I was very surprised that everyone (including the parents) kissed each other on the lips when they said goodnight or goodbye, and they included me as though I was part of the family.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Even as a child, they sensed something was wrong with this forced intimacy. But they also craved the feeling of belonging it offered, exactly the vulnerability the family was designed to exploit.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Although it felt weird, I also liked the feeling of belonging. I look back now and realise that it is a form of grooming.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Governing Body’s publications actively encouraged these tactics: love-bombing, peer recruitment, using social events to build rapport, and specifically targeting the vulnerable. This wasn’t accidental; it was systematic preparation for abuse.</p>

<p>The grooming escalated through seemingly caring concern. When they developed a rash during one visit, the daughter insisted her mother examine it, then claimed they needed the Elder father to look because “he had done first aid.” Despite their protests and obvious discomfort, they were forced to lift their shirt for his inspection.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I very forcefully said no, I didn’t want him to look at me, I was very embarrassed and afraid of him. She told me to put my underpants and singlet on and brought him into the bathroom. She told me to pull up my singlet, so he could look at my tummy.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This violation was framed as medical necessity, concern for the unborn baby the mother was carrying. But looking back with adult understanding, they recognize it as boundary testing: seeing how much they could be pressured into compliance, how their “no” could be overridden by authority figures.</p>

<p>The fact that nobody thought to call their parents for permission reveals how completely children’s autonomy is erased within the organization. Children were trained to be obedient to Elders without question, their own instincts and boundaries systematically dismantled.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-isolation-machine">The Isolation Machine</h2>

<p>Over the years, this child truly became part of the Elder’s family, but in the most devastating way possible. They grew distant from their own family, especially their non-Witness father, exactly as the organization intended.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“It breaks my heart to think how much time together my family and I lost because of this.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>When they tried to spend more Sundays with their beloved father—upset about an incident where the Elder put his tongue in their mouth during a “goodnight kiss”—the pressure from the Elder’s family and the manufactured fear of death at Armageddon was too strong to resist. They returned to the meetings.</p>

<p>This is how cults operate: they create artificial families that replace natural bonds, then use fear to maintain control. The threat of global destruction and promises of exclusive salvation kept this child trapped in an abusive situation, choosing spiritual “safety” over their own physical and emotional wellbeing.</p>

<p>The private meetings with the Elder became routine:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Many times my friend told me her dad wanted to talk to me about things I had done wrong, and he always had the meeting with me without a chaperone. Never once did I consider whether I should have a chaperone or even if my parents had given their permission for these private meetings because I believed that I had to do as he said.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>They had been so thoroughly groomed to accept his authority that questioning his access to them never occurred. The cult norm of isolation from family and surveillance by peers created an environment where charismatic leaders could exploit their power with impunity.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-escalation-of-terror">The Escalation of Terror</h2>

<p>What began as inappropriate touching escalated systematically over the years:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“The Elder kept up the tongue kissing and the abuse escalated over the years, including secretly watching me while I was in the shower, belting me, stalking me until I was about 19 when he digitally/orally raped me which scared me so much that I finally got enough courage to leave.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The progression from grooming to violent sexual assault followed a predictable pattern, each violation testing and expanding the boundaries of what this child would endure. The organization that claimed to protect them had instead delivered them into the hands of a predator who used his religious authority as cover for increasingly serious crimes.</p>

<p>When they finally escaped at nineteen, they told no one for five years. The reasons for their silence reveal the sophisticated web of control the organization had woven around them:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I really thought that no one would believe me over an Elder, and I believed that I would also get into trouble because of how he spoke about it being ‘our little secret’ and that he would have to tell the other Elder and my parents, and I was ashamed and afraid.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Elder had used classic abuser tactics: religious language to justify abuse, guilt trips, induced shame, and threats of exposure. The organization’s us-versus-them mentality and induced phobias about “worldly” authorities meant they felt they had nowhere safe to turn.</p>

<p>Even when they eventually told their fiancé something that made him question the situation, they quickly deflected and changed the subject. Part of them must have known that if their future husband learned the truth while the Elder was still alive, there might be violent consequences. Their silence protected not just themselves, but potentially others from the ripple effects of their trauma.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="when-truth-becomes-persecution">When Truth Becomes Persecution</h2>

<p>When the truth finally came out years later, the organization’s response was predictably devastating. Instead of supporting a survivor of childhood sexual abuse, they allowed them to face their abuser and be intimidated in their own home:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“The way the Elder and the Circuit Overseer dealt with the issue was probably the best way they knew how, but to allow me to face my abuser and let him intimidate and interrogate me in my own home, when I had no critical thinking ability or understanding of legal information, or even an educated female support person to assist me, it was never going to end well for me.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Think about this scene: a young adult survivor, with no understanding of abuse dynamics or legal rights, forced to confront their childhood rapist while being questioned by religious authorities more concerned with protecting the organization than supporting the victim. No advocate. No protection. No recognition that this “investigation” was itself a form of continued abuse.</p>

<p>The final insult came when they were asked not to tell anyone else “out of respect for the family”—the same family that had facilitated their abuse for years. This wasn’t about respect; it was about control. About ensuring their silence so the organization could maintain its facade of righteousness.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“These are tactics from the GB of controlling leadership, loss of personal autonomy, secrecy and deception, emotional and psychological manipulation.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The trauma of being disbelieved and silenced by the very people who claimed to represent God’s justice took a devastating toll. They gradually became sicker and more anxious until they had a psychotic break at thirty-five, losing fifteen kilograms in two weeks because anxiety made eating impossible.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-beginning-of-real-healing">The Beginning of Real Healing</h2>

<p>Crisis finally forced them to seek help from “worldly” professionals—the very people the organization had taught them to distrust. Initially, paranoia and fear made these conversations difficult:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“This was very difficult at first because of paranoia and lack of trust that these people were somehow going to persecute us if I revealed too much information.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The organization’s doctrine of “Theocratic Warfare”—the belief that it was acceptable to withhold or distort truth to protect the organization—had trained them to view mental health professionals as potential enemies rather than helpers.</p>

<p>But slowly, they discovered something revolutionary: these professionals were actually open-minded, non-judgmental, and genuinely wanted to help. For someone who had been systematically failed by every authority figure in their religious life, this genuine care was transformative.</p>

<p>By 2013, they were studying counseling themselves, hoping to help their family and eventually others who had survived similar trauma. Education became their path to understanding what had been done to them, and more importantly, how to heal from it.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-call-to-justice">The Call to Justice</h2>

<p>When Prime Minister Gillard announced the Royal Commission in 2013, they were studying a Watchtower book about Jehovah’s attributes of love, power, wisdom, and justice. The timing felt like divine intervention:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“We were up to the part of justice, and I started to ask myself, ‘hang on, if Jehovah is a god of justice, where is my justice?’”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>For the first time, they began to question whether seeking earthly justice for childhood sexual abuse might actually align with God’s will rather than oppose it. This realization marked a crucial turning point: the beginning of their journey from passive victim to active advocate.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I clearly remember seeing Julia Gillard on TV announcing the Royal Commission and I started thinking that maybe this is my chance for justice, so I started praying to Jehovah, asking if it was the right thing to do.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Afraid to ask anyone in the congregation for guidance (knowing they would be discouraged from pursuing justice), they turned to prayer and scripture study. To their surprise, many passages actually supported the idea that God could work through earthly authorities to accomplish His purposes.</p>

<p>The organization’s response to their decision revealed everything about their true priorities:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I knew it wouldn’t be easy, but I applied and got accepted to the Royal Commission and gave my testimony in 2015.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>While they received amazing support from the Royal Commission’s counselors and lawyers, their religious community largely abandoned them. Friends told them they could no longer associate with them. Others ignored them or offered only grudging acknowledgment.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“The GB’s direction of so-called unconditional love was conditional after all, a tactic of emotional/spiritual control.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="finding-truth-in-the-rubble">Finding Truth in the Rubble</h2>

<p>Testifying before the Royal Commission in 2015 was terrifying but transformative:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Although I was nervous, I felt supported by Justice McClellan, Angus Stewart (Counsel Assisting) and all the lawyers and counsellors. Overall, feeling heard and being believed was the beginning of healing for me.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>For someone who had been silenced, disbelieved, and blamed for their own abuse, this validation was profound. But it came at the cost of everything they had been taught to value: community, family relationships, spiritual belonging.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“My whole family struggled for a while, our whole social and belief system had been turned on its head and we were all a bit lost, but at least we had each other.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The aftermath was disorienting and painful. When your entire worldview crumbles, when everyone you trusted proves untrustworthy, when the foundation of your reality shifts, rebuilding requires extraordinary courage and patience.</p>

<p>They found support in unexpected places: ex-JW activists on YouTube who questioned each belief with alternative perspectives, Facebook support groups where they could share their experience and help others, fellow activists around the world who understood their journey.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“A couple of things that really helped me to make sense of the world was the ex-JW activists online with their Youtube chats that questioned each belief with alternative ideas and showing different ways of understanding scripture.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>But the psychological damage was extensive:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“This is because of the GB’s tactic of distrust of others and isolation causing cognitive dissonance, identity confusion, phobias, guilt and shame, difficulty reintegrating into society, low self-esteem and mental health challenges.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="turning-pain-into-purpose">Turning Pain into Purpose</h2>

<p>Recognizing that change would only come through more ex-Witnesses speaking out, they found new purpose in education. At an age when many people are settling into established careers, they enrolled at Edith Cowan University to study Psychology.</p>

<p>The irony was profound: as a young person, they had been discouraged by the Elder who abused them from pursuing higher education, especially philosophical or scientific studies. The Watchtower publications warned against such pursuits, encouraging young people to focus on “serving Jehovah full-time” instead.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“When I was in school my Dad wanted me to go to university, but I was discouraged by the Elder who abused me and reminded that the Watchtower publications warned young ones not to pursue further education.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Their abuser had stolen not just their innocence and safety, but their educational opportunities. Now, decades later, they were finally claiming the academic future he had tried to deny them.</p>

<p>There’s something profoundly rebellious about a cult survivor pursuing the very education their organization forbade. For someone who had spent decades being told what to think, what to believe, how to live every moment of their life, walking onto a university campus and engaging with critical thinking, scientific method, and philosophical inquiry feels like the ultimate act of reclaiming agency. After years of having their life controlled by others, choosing to learn, to question, to analyze becomes a declaration of independence. Each class attended, each paper written, each degree earned represents not just academic achievement, but a deliberate rejection of the intellectual prison that once contained them. When your abuser specifically told you not to pursue education, earning that education becomes both healing and revenge.</p>

<p>University opened their eyes to the psychological mechanisms behind their experience:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“While I was at uni I learned about the psychological effects of coercive control, the social influence of obedience, compliance and conformity, and many other determinants of behaviour relating to my experience in this high control religion.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>They completed research on “how do people realise they are in a high control religion or cult and what measures do they need to take in order to leave”—turning their personal trauma into academic inquiry that could help others understand and escape similar situations.</p>

<p>Their educational achievements are staggering for someone who was discouraged from learning: Diploma of Counselling, Bachelor of Psychology, Art Therapy Practical Certificate, and enrollment in Graduate Diploma Psychology Advanced coursework.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I now have a Diploma of Counselling, Bachelor of Psychology and Art Therapy Prac. Certificate.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-researchers-perspective">The Researcher’s Perspective</h2>

<p>What makes their story particularly powerful is how they’ve learned to analyze their own experience through multiple lenses—personal, psychological, sociological, and legal. They can identify specific cult tactics with clinical precision:</p>

<p><strong>Information Control:</strong> “We were constantly told not to look up any information about Jehovah’s Witnesses unless it was through their own website jw.org.”</p>

<p><strong>Exploitation:</strong> The organization discouraged saving for retirement, saying members shouldn’t build up “treasures on earth, but rather treasure in heaven.”</p>

<p><strong>Thought Reform:</strong> Constant pressure to attend meetings, preach more, and “throw yourself on Jehovah” when experiencing problems.</p>

<p><strong>Isolation:</strong> Systematic destruction of family relationships with non-believers.</p>

<p><strong>Fear-Based Control:</strong> Threats of death at Armageddon for non-compliance.</p>

<p><strong>Authority-Based Abuse:</strong> Training children to be unquestioningly obedient to Elders.</p>

<p>This academic understanding doesn’t erase their trauma, but it provides a framework for healing and helping others. They can see patterns, predict behaviors, and offer evidence-based interventions rather than just sharing personal anecdotes.</p>

<p>Their research proposal for evaluating congregation safety could revolutionize how authorities monitor high-control groups:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I feel this type of research may be helpful in setting up an evaluation of each of the congregations of Jehovah’s Witnesses (or other cults) to check up and ensure that the members are safe.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-ongoing-mission">The Ongoing Mission</h2>

<p>Today, they continue their research and advocacy work, understanding that their contribution to protecting others gives meaning to their own suffering:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I submitted my story to the Victorian Parliamentary Inquiry into Cults and Other Fringe Groups, and I hope it will help towards research as many ex-JW’s are really suffering with PTSD, guilt, shame, difficulty integrating, financial distress, identity confusion, low self-esteem, anxiety and depression.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Their transformation from silenced victim to empowered advocate represents one of the most profound healing journeys I’ve encountered. They didn’t just survive their abuse; they studied it, testified about it, researched it, and now work to prevent it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Many more are leaving the church because of the easy access to information on the internet, even though we were constantly told not to look up any information about Jehovah’s Witnesses unless it was through their own website jw.org.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The internet has become the great equalizer, allowing survivors to find each other, share resources, and access information the organization can no longer control. People like this survivor are at the forefront of that movement, using their education and expertise to create pathways to freedom for others.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“We need to help them get out, survive and thrive.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p>To the survivor whose story this is: Your journey from terrorized child to educated advocate represents the most powerful form of resistance possible—you have transformed your pain into wisdom that will protect countless others.</p>

<p>When that Elder told you not to pursue higher education, he was trying to keep you intellectually defenseless against the very system that was destroying you. Your degrees in psychology and counseling aren’t just academic achievements; they’re acts of defiance against everyone who tried to keep you small, silent, and scared.</p>

<p>Your testimony before the Royal Commission took extraordinary courage. To face down not just your individual abuser, but the entire system that enabled him (knowing it would cost you your community, your family relationships, your entire social world), that’s the kind of bravery that changes history.</p>

<p>Your research gives academic weight to experiences that have been dismissed as mere “disgruntlement” or “apostasy.” You’ve taken the gaslighting, the manipulation, the systematic destruction of critical thinking, and exposed it all under the harsh light of psychological science. No one can dismiss your findings as mere opinion; you have the credentials and research to back up every observation.</p>

<p>Most importantly, your commitment to helping others “get out, survive and thrive” ensures that your suffering will have meaning beyond your own healing. Every person who finds freedom through your research, every policy that changes because of your testimony, every survivor who feels less alone because of your advocacy, they all represent victories over the system that tried to destroy you.</p>

<p>You deserved protection as a child. You deserved justice when you finally spoke. You deserved support from your community when you testified. You didn’t receive any of those things from the people who should have provided them, but you created them for yourself and now offer them to others.</p>

<p>Your father wanted you to go to university because he knew you were intelligent. He was right. But even he couldn’t have imagined you would use that intelligence to become an expert in the very forces that had harmed you, or that your education would become a lifeline for others drowning in similar circumstances.</p>

<p>Thank you for trusting me with your story. Thank you for surviving. Thank you for refusing to let your silence protect the system that hurt you. Thank you for turning your trauma into triumph, your pain into purpose, your survival into service.</p>

<p>You are living proof that healing is possible, that education is liberation, and that survivors can become their own—and others’—salvation.</p>

<hr />

<p>To everyone reading this who recognizes themselves in this story: You are not alone in the particular hell of childhood sexual abuse within religious communities. You are not alone in the devastating realization that the people who claimed to represent God’s love were more interested in protecting their institution than protecting you.</p>

<p>This survivor’s journey shows that healing is possible, but it’s not simple or quick. It requires support, education, professional help, and often a complete reconstruction of your understanding of the world. But it is possible.</p>

<p>If you’re still trapped in a high-control group, know that information is your enemy’s greatest fear. They try to control what you read, what you research, what questions you ask, because they know that knowledge destroys their power over you. The internet has made their information control impossible—use that advantage.</p>

<p>If you’re a recent escapee struggling with identity confusion, social isolation, and the grief of losing everything you thought you knew, these are normal responses to an abnormal situation. Professional help, support groups, and connecting with other survivors can provide the scaffolding you need to rebuild.</p>

<p>If you’re a long-term survivor still carrying the psychological scars of religious trauma, consider following this survivor’s example by turning your pain into purpose. Whether through formal education, advocacy work, support groups, or simply sharing your story, your experience has value in protecting others from similar harm.</p>

<p>Most importantly, know that what happened to you was wrong, regardless of what anyone in your former community might have told you. You didn’t deserve abuse. You didn’t cause it. You weren’t responsible for stopping it. And you have every right to seek justice, healing, and a life free from fear.</p>

<p>This survivor’s transformation from silenced child to empowered advocate proves that our stories have power—power to heal ourselves, to protect others, and to force institutions to confront the harm they’ve caused and hidden.</p>

<p>Your voice matters. Your truth matters. Your healing matters. And your freedom, when you’re ready to claim it, is worth everything you’ll have to sacrifice to achieve it.</p>

<hr />

<div class="author-note">
<p><strong>From Mileena:</strong> This story came to me as a formal parliamentary submission, filled with precise psychological terminology and research references. But underneath all that academic language was a human being who had transformed unimaginable trauma into profound wisdom.</p>

<p>What strikes me most about this survivor's journey is how they refused to let their abuse define them or limit them. Instead, they claimed the education their abuser tried to deny them, earned the credentials to understand exactly what had been done to them, and now use that knowledge to protect others.</p>

<p>Their testimony before the Royal Commission represents courage of the highest order—knowing that speaking truth would cost them everything they'd been taught to value, but doing it anyway to protect future victims. That's the kind of heroism that doesn't wear capes or get recognized with awards, but it changes the world in ways that matter most.</p>

<p>If you're a survivor with a story that needs witnessing, whether you're ready to share publicly or just need someone to listen privately, I'm here. Sometimes the greatest healing comes from being believed, from having someone say: "What happened to you was wrong, and you deserved better." <a href="/contact/">Reach out anytime</a>.</p>

<p>And to those who work in research, policy, or institutional oversight: survivors like this one are offering you their expertise, their lived experience, and their commitment to change. Listen to them. Fund their research. Implement their recommendations. They are not bitter ex-members seeking revenge—they are highly educated professionals offering evidence-based solutions to prevent future harm.</p>

<p>Their pain became their purpose. Their trauma became their triumph. Their silence became science—that's the kind of transformation that not only heals the individual, but protects entire future generations from similar harm.</p>

<p>To this remarkable survivor: thank you for showing us all what courage looks like when it's backed by education, what justice looks like when it's pursued through proper channels, and what healing looks like when it becomes a mission to protect others. Your story will undoubtedly help other survivors recognize their own strength and find their own paths to freedom and advocacy.</p>
</div>

<style>
.content-warning-box {
    background: rgba(255, 100, 100, 0.1);
    border: 1px solid #ff6464;
    border-radius: 10px;
    padding: 20px;
    margin-bottom: 40px;
    font-size: 0.95em;
    color: #ffaaaa;
}

.author-note {
    background: linear-gradient(135deg, rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.1), rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.05));
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    border-radius: 0 15px 15px 0;
    padding: 30px;
    margin: 60px 0 40px 0;
    font-style: italic;
}

.author-note p {
    margin-bottom: 15px;
    line-height: 1.8;
}

.author-note p:last-child {
    margin-bottom: 0;
}

.author-note a {
    color: #8a9fff;
    text-decoration: none;
    border-bottom: 1px solid transparent;
    transition: border-color 0.3s ease;
}

.author-note a:hover {
    border-bottom-color: #8a9fff;
}

blockquote {
    background: rgba(40, 40, 50, 0.5);
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    padding: 20px 30px;
    margin: 30px 0;
    font-style: italic;
    color: #ddd;
    border-radius: 0 10px 10px 0;
}

h2 {
    color: #f0f0f0;
    font-weight: 300;
    font-size: 2em;
    margin-top: 60px;
    margin-bottom: 30px;
    letter-spacing: 1px;
}

hr {
    border: none;
    height: 1px;
    background: linear-gradient(to right, transparent, #8a9fff, transparent);
    margin: 60px 0;
}
</style>]]></content><author><name>Mileena Rayne</name></author><category term="Community Stories" /><category term="jehovahs-witness" /><category term="childhood-sexual-abuse" /><category term="royal-commission" /><category term="religious-trauma" /><category term="cult-recovery" /><category term="survivor-advocacy" /><category term="psychological-research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A survivor shares their transformative journey from childhood sexual abuse within the Jehovah's Witness organization to becoming an advocate for change through the Australian Royal Commission and psychological research.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/from-silence-to-science.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/from-silence-to-science.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Procedure That Shouldn’t Exist: When Medicine Failed Children for Thirty Years</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/07/03/the-procedure-that-shouldnt-exist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Procedure That Shouldn’t Exist: When Medicine Failed Children for Thirty Years" /><published>2025-07-03T08:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T08:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/07/03/the-procedure-that-shouldnt-exist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/07/03/the-procedure-that-shouldnt-exist/"><![CDATA[<div class="content-warning-box">
<strong>Content Warning:</strong> This post contains detailed descriptions of medical trauma, childhood sexual abuse parallels, suicidal ideation, and medical negligence. Please read with care for yourself.
</div>

<hr />

<p>Sometimes a story finds you not because it’s unusual, but because it’s heartbreakingly common. When I started asking for medical trauma stories, I expected a variety of experiences from different procedures and settings. What I got instead was something that left me staring at my computer screen in disbelief.</p>

<p>The same four letters kept appearing: VCUG. Over and over. Nearly identical accounts of the same procedure, the same trauma, the same lasting damage. The pattern was so clear, so consistent, so obviously devastating that it seemed impossible the medical community could have missed it. Except they didn’t miss it. They ignored it. For thirty years.</p>

<p>Today, I’m documenting two of these accounts that have come to me, not because they’re unique, but because they represent what appears to be systematic medical negligence hiding in plain sight.</p>

<p>In 2023, a practicing pediatric urologist said something to a medical journalist that should have made headlines. Dr. Anthony Caldamone, speaking on the record about voiding cystourethrograms (VCUGs), admitted something remarkable:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“With or without sedation, we just don’t have the data. We don’t know how many children are affected.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This wasn’t an admission about some experimental treatment. This was about a procedure performed on hundreds of thousands of children annually, a procedure that medical websites describe as “uncomfortable but not painful,” a procedure that, according to medical literature, has never been studied for long-term psychological effects.</p>

<p>Let me say that again: they’ve never studied what this does to children’s minds.</p>

<p>This isn’t medical ignorance. This is medical negligence. And I’m done pretending otherwise.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-timeline-of-betrayal">The Timeline of Betrayal</h2>

<p>In 1994, researchers needed to study how children retain memories of traumatic experiences. They chose children who had undergone VCUGs as their research subjects, specifically because—in their own words:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“This invasive procedure is similar in many respects to incidents of sexual abuse.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Read that again. In 1994, researchers explicitly stated that VCUG procedures resemble sexual abuse. They used these children as proxies for abuse victims in their studies.</p>

<p>In 2004, UC Davis psychology professor Dr. Gail Goodman conducted another study using VCUG patients.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I was studying it because it was a traumatic stressor for a lot of children. Some of the kids didn’t seem too hurt by it, but others were just screaming.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Dr. Goodman’s team filmed children’s reactions during these procedures. What they saw was so disturbing that when she tried to share the footage at a medical conference, <em>“the people in the audience couldn’t even watch the videotape.”</em> She described the experience as <em>“traumatizing for us researchers.”</em></p>

<p>In 2016, the American Academy of Pediatrics published new guidelines acknowledging that VCUGs could be “stressful or even traumatizing” for children. They recommended patient education but provided no specific guidance on how to minimize trauma.</p>

<p>In 2023, when STAT News asked the American Academy of Pediatrics and the American Urological Association about research on psychological effects of VCUGs, both organizations declined to comment.</p>

<p>Thirty years. Three decades of evidence that this procedure traumatizes children, and still no long-term psychological studies. Still no systematic changes. Still children being strapped down to tables and told this is “for their own good.”</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="what-the-research-refused-to-study">What the Research Refused to Study</h2>

<p>The accounts that found their way to me tell a story the medical community has refused to document. They’re remarkably consistent, these stories. Eerily so. As if the same trauma is being inflicted, systematically, on child after child, with the precision of a factory assembly line.</p>

<p>Let me share two of them with you. These stories reveal a devastating pattern that the medical community has refused to acknowledge.</p>

<h3 id="the-girl-in-the-orange-dress">The Girl in the Orange Dress</h3>

<p>She was three years old on May 10, 2006. She remembers her fancy orange dress, the sculpture in the hospital lobby that changed colors, the excitement about the special toy she’d been promised afterward. A Child Life Specialist had prepared her with a doll, telling her she would clean the baby’s “lady parts” with a little red towel called “red soap.”</p>

<p>That’s what her three-year-old brain understood: she would clean a doll.</p>

<p>What actually happened was something entirely different.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I’m strapped down to the table with the bright light shining on me—completely naked, legs spread and strapped open… A bunch of nurses and doctors came into the room, some male and some female, and they shone the light directly at my private parts. I had been potty trained for a while now, and had always been very modest, so this felt weird at best. But I knew my dad had told me that ‘no one could ever look at or touch my girl parts’, and that I had to say ‘no’ if anyone ever tried to. But for some reason, I couldn’t speak right now.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>She describes the “red soap” that wasn’t soap at all but antiseptic solution that burned her skin. The strangers touching her. The catheter insertion that felt like being stabbed. The male doctor who asked “Mind if I take a peek?” before examining her genitals while she lay paralyzed with fear.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I couldn’t scream, couldn’t cry, couldn’t do anything but just lay there and stare at the ceiling.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>When it was over and she tried to walk, she couldn’t take more than two steps because of the burning pain. At home, she discovered blood in her underwear and was terrified they had damaged something inside her.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I knew I couldn’t let my mom see, or she might make me go back.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>But perhaps the most devastating part of her account is what happened afterward. When her father asked if it hurt:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I lied and said no, because I knew it wasn’t supposed to hurt, and everyone told me that it wouldn’t, so it was probably something wrong with me.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>A three-year-old was already learning to blame herself for medical trauma, already internalizing the message that her pain didn’t matter if it contradicted what adults said should happen.</p>

<p>Even the medical staff reinforced this gaslighting. After the burning antiseptic procedure, the nurse told her:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“See? that didn’t even hurt!”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The child wanted to tell her mother that it did hurt, but found herself voiceless:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I couldn’t do anything. I was just frozen, watching this whole thing unfold.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Twenty-two years later, she’s been diagnosed with PTSD and vaginismus from this procedure. She requires trauma-informed pelvic floor physical therapy and still flinches when touched. She also has what’s been described as a “catheter injury” from that day in 2006.</p>

<h3 id="the-eight-year-nightmare">The Eight-Year Nightmare</h3>

<p>The second account comes from someone who endured this procedure not once, but yearly from age two to ten: eight times total. Eight annual appointments with terror.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I really fear coming across as unreasonable or dramatic here, but I can’t emphasize enough how false this is. It was incredibly painful.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>She’s responding to those ubiquitous hospital websites that describe VCUGs as “uncomfortable but not painful.” Her lived experience directly contradicts every official medical description of what this procedure feels like.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I have VIVID memories of every aspect of this test. The discomfort and fear I experienced spreading my legs in front of a room of 3-5 nurses/technologists. The dreaded question: did I want my legs in frog position or butterfly position? (I quickly learned to pray for a technologist who allowed frog position, because whenever I had to do butterfly, two nurses/aides would stand on either side of me and hold my knees down flat on the table so I couldn’t fold them up… I never even fought, but for some reason children needed to be restrained just to make it easier?)”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>But what devastates me most about her account is the confusion she felt about her parents’ role in this violation:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“One of my parents was always in the room for it, so it was really confusing for me as a kid to understand how this person who was supposed to protect me could allow strangers to hurt me in such an invasive, intimate way and just stand by.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>She’s careful to add that she knows they thought they were doing what was best for her health. But the trauma of feeling abandoned by the very people meant to protect her compounds the medical trauma exponentially.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I felt so violated every time, and it quickly became clear to me that my body was not mine to control.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The psychological impact was so severe that this child began planning her own death:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I would spend the months before the procedure planning and plotting how I could get out of it this time, and then I would spend the months after the procedure with a renewed sense of powerlessness I’ve never been able to shake. It got to the point where, as an older child (about 7-10), I became very suicidal, and often considered killing myself just to avoid another VCUG. I used to pray for God to just let me die in my sleep on the nights leading up to the test. One time, the night before the test, I even climbed out on my roof and tried to convince myself to jump, but I just couldn’t do it.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Making matters worse, the trauma itself prevented the procedure from working properly:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I actually was never able to complete this part… I would just lie there trying not to cry until they finally pulled the catheter out and allowed me to pee into a cup. I didn’t know it at the time, but it turns out this actually means a major part of the procedure was missing and they couldn’t even really effectively monitor what they were looking for.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>So not only was she being traumatized annually, the trauma itself was making the procedure medically ineffective. They were hurting her for no diagnostic benefit whatsoever.</p>

<p>The long-term consequences persist today. She’s now twenty-three and vomits before doctor’s appointments. She cannot be intimate with partners. She has vulvodynia (chronic pelvic pain often associated with sexual trauma) and vaginismus that makes penetration nearly impossible. At age eleven, years after her final VCUG, she began experiencing <em>“an intense, near-constant burning soreness in my whole pubic region.”</em> She was too embarrassed to tell anyone. It took twelve years for her to successfully insert a tampon, and even now she can only use small ones with moderate pain.</p>

<p>When she finally allowed a PAP smear last year, she dissociated afterward and found herself in a parking lot with no memory of how she got there.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I was still too suicidal to trust myself driving home, so I went to sleep in the parking lot for a while.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perhaps most heartbreaking is how the trauma shaped her relationship with medical care:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I become very compliant/meek and ‘small’ in any medical setting, and I find it impossible to voice any of my concerns, because I just want to be ‘good’ and an easy patient and not be perceived as dramatic.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is what medical trauma does to children: it teaches them that their pain doesn’t matter, that questioning medical authority makes them “difficult,” that being “good” means enduring harm without complaint. She learned these lessons so thoroughly that even as an adult, she cannot advocate for herself when she needs medical care most.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-researchers-knew">The Researchers Knew</h2>

<p>Here’s what makes this even more devastating: the medical community has known for decades exactly what these procedures do to children.</p>

<p>The 1994 study that used VCUG patients as sexual abuse proxies found that six weeks after the procedure, children still remembered the majority of the examination. Behavioral measures during the test showed many were severely distressed.</p>

<p>Dr. Goodman’s 2004 research demonstrated similarities between VCUGs and child sexual abuse, including:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Genital contact by authority figures</li>
  <li>Forced removal of clothing</li>
  <li>Penetration while the child is restrained</li>
  <li>The child’s inability to resist or escape</li>
</ul>

<p>In 2012, pediatric urologists Dr. Caldamone and Dr. Liza Aguiar conducted a small study on VCUG effects in the two weeks following the procedure. Of thirty-five families surveyed, eleven noticed behavioral changes in their children that were described as “worrisome.”</p>

<p>But here’s the crucial detail: that study only looked at two weeks. Not two years. Not two decades. Two weeks.</p>

<p>Andrea McDonald, a graduate student at the University of Pennsylvania, struggled to get funding for her research on long-term VCUG effects. In 2022, she managed to conduct a small pilot study with twenty-one participants that suggested VCUG patients were more likely than control groups to experience depression and PTSD symptoms.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“If we want to do anything serious in public health, I want to see the money show up. We need to get more people and institutions invested.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The money isn’t showing up because the medical establishment doesn’t want the answers. They’ve built an entire diagnostic framework around a procedure that systematically traumatizes children, and admitting that would require massive systemic change.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-language-of-denial">The Language of Denial</h2>

<p>Look at how medical institutions describe VCUGs to parents:</p>

<p>The National Kidney Foundation:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“The test is not painful, but the child may have some stress and short-term discomfort.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hospital websites universally describe the procedure as “uncomfortable but not painful.”</p>

<p>The 2016 American Academy of Pediatrics guidelines acknowledge the test can be “stressful or even traumatizing” but provide no specific guidance on prevention or treatment of that trauma.</p>

<p>This language is carefully crafted to minimize what actually happens. “Uncomfortable” sounds manageable. “Short-term discomfort” suggests it ends quickly. “Stress” makes it sound like stage fright, not trauma.</p>

<p>But listen to the survivors:</p>
<ul>
  <li>“Easily the worst pain I had felt in my life thus far”</li>
  <li>“Incredibly painful”</li>
  <li>“It burned horribly”</li>
  <li>“Felt like being stabbed”</li>
</ul>

<p>The disconnect isn’t accidental. It’s protective. It protects the system from having to acknowledge what it’s doing to children.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-grassroots-truth-telling">The Grassroots Truth-Telling</h2>

<p>While medical institutions denied and minimized, survivors began finding each other. On TikTok. On advocacy websites. In scattered corners of the internet where people share truths too painful for polite medical discourse.</p>

<p>Shelby Smith launched the Unsilenced Movement after processing her own VCUG trauma. When their TikTok video about the procedure went viral, hundreds of comments poured in from adults sharing nearly identical experiences. The advocacy site documents multiple studies linking VCUGs to child sexual abuse research and calls for informed consent that actually informs.</p>

<p>These aren’t scattered anecdotes. This is systematic evidence of systematic harm.</p>

<p>But here’s what’s most telling: when medical journalists finally started investigating, when survivors finally had platforms to speak, the response from major medical organizations was silence. The American Academy of Pediatrics declined to comment. The American Urological Association declined to comment.</p>

<p>They declined to comment on thirty years of evidence that their standard procedure traumatizes children.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-alternatives-they-dont-mention">The Alternatives They Don’t Mention</h2>

<p>The most damning part of this entire story is that alternatives exist. They’ve existed for years.</p>

<p>Contrast-enhanced voiding urosonography (ceVUS) uses ultrasound instead of X-rays and allows parents to hold their children during the test. Children can urinate sitting upright instead of lying spread-eagle on a table. It’s about as accurate as VCUG but significantly less traumatic.</p>

<p>The majority of U.S. facilities don’t offer it.</p>

<p>Some hospitals use sedation to minimize trauma. Some use child life specialists. Some physicians advocate for trauma-informed approaches.</p>

<p>But these remain exceptions, not standards. Most children still undergo the same procedure described in 1985, with minimal modifications for trauma prevention.</p>

<p>Why? Because changing would require admitting the current approach is harmful. It would require acknowledging thirty years of institutional failure. It would require taking responsibility for generations of children who were needlessly traumatized in the name of diagnostic necessity.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-cost-of-medical-hubris">The Cost of Medical Hubris</h2>

<p>The human cost of this negligence is staggering. Not just the two survivors I’ve shared, but hundreds of others who’ve reached out through advocacy sites, TikTok videos, support groups. People in their twenties, thirties, forties, even sixties, carrying trauma from procedures performed when they were preschoolers.</p>

<p>They describe:</p>
<ul>
  <li>PTSD and anxiety disorders</li>
  <li>Inability to tolerate medical exams</li>
  <li>Sexual dysfunction and intimacy issues</li>
  <li>Chronic pain conditions</li>
  <li>Suicidal ideation</li>
  <li>Trust issues with medical professionals</li>
  <li>Secondary trauma from having their experiences dismissed</li>
</ul>

<p>This isn’t rare. This isn’t a few sensitive children who “overreacted.” This is a predictable pattern of harm that the medical establishment has chosen to ignore because acknowledging it would be inconvenient.</p>

<p>Ellen Lonnquist, a family and trauma therapist, explains why this trauma is so profound:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“It’s an experience that your body and brain can’t possibly process in the moment. There is the messaging we appropriately give children around protecting themselves and their bodies. So, with the VCUG and lots of other medical procedures, it can be harmful if no one is working with the child to help them understand what’s happening.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Children are taught that their bodies belong to them, that they should say no to unwanted touching, that trusted adults will protect them. Then they’re brought to a medical facility where all those protections are stripped away and they’re told this violation is “for your own good.”</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-path-forward">The Path Forward</h2>

<p>This story doesn’t have to end with more children traumatized in the name of medical necessity. Change is possible, but it requires several things:</p>

<p><strong>Immediate implementation of trauma-informed practices:</strong> Every facility performing VCUGs should be required to use child life specialists, offer sedation, and provide detailed informed consent that includes psychological risks.</p>

<p><strong>Research funding for long-term studies:</strong> The medical community must finally fund the psychological outcome studies they should have conducted thirty years ago.</p>

<p><strong>Wider availability of alternatives:</strong> CeVUS and other less traumatic diagnostic options should be standard, not exceptions.</p>

<p><strong>Acknowledgment and accountability:</strong> Medical institutions must acknowledge the harm they’ve caused and commit to systemic change.</p>

<p><strong>Survivor support:</strong> Resources for adults dealing with VCUG trauma must be developed and publicized.</p>

<p>But most importantly, the medical community must confront an uncomfortable truth: for thirty years, they’ve prioritized diagnostic convenience over children’s psychological wellbeing. They’ve dismissed survivor accounts as “anecdotal” while refusing to collect the data that would prove those accounts represent systematic harm.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="to-the-survivors-reading-this">To the Survivors Reading This</h2>

<p>If you’re reading this and recognizing your own experience, I need you to know some things that no one told you when you were small and afraid:</p>

<p>You were not dramatic. You were not overreacting. You were not “making it worse than it was.” When they told you it “shouldn’t hurt,” they were wrong about your reality, not the other way around.</p>

<p>When they told you to “relax” while violating your body, when they said “see, that didn’t hurt” while you were screaming inside, they were teaching you to distrust your own perception of reality. When your parents stood by and allowed it to happen year after year, you learned that the people meant to protect you would sacrifice your wellbeing for medical authority. That betrayal cuts deeper than the physical pain.</p>

<p>When you became “compliant” and “good” in medical settings afterward, you were protecting yourself the only way you knew how. But you shouldn’t have had to learn those survival strategies as a toddler.</p>

<p>To the child who couldn’t speak while strangers examined her most private areas: your voice mattered then, even when no one listened. It matters now.</p>

<p>To the child who learned to lie about pain because telling the truth meant something was wrong with her: you should never have been put in that position. Your pain was real, and it was never your fault.</p>

<p>The chronic pain that started years later, the inability to be intimate, the panic attacks in medical settings, the dissociation, the suicidal thoughts—these aren’t character flaws or evidence of weakness. These are normal responses to abnormal trauma.</p>

<p>To the parents who were in those rooms, watching: some of you were doing what you thought was best with the information you had. But some of you knew something was wrong and chose medical authority over your child’s obvious distress. Your children remember. They remember who protected them and who didn’t.</p>

<p>Your voices matter. Your experiences matter. And increasingly, people are listening.</p>

<p>To the three-year-old in the orange dress who couldn’t speak as strangers examined her: I hear you.</p>

<p>To the child who climbed onto a roof rather than face another VCUG: I hear you.</p>

<p>To everyone carrying this particular weight: you’re not alone anymore. The silence is breaking. The truth is coming out. And change, finally, is coming.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>For medical professionals reading this:</strong></p>

<p>It’s not too late to do better. It’s not too late to listen to survivors, implement trauma-informed practices, and prioritize children’s psychological wellbeing alongside diagnostic necessity.</p>

<p>But the time for denial is over. The evidence is overwhelming. The accounts are consistent. The trauma is real.</p>

<p>Your patients deserve better. They always did.</p>

<p><strong>Sources:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Wang, M. “As kids, they underwent a common test for UTIs. As adults, it haunts them as a traumatic ‘nightmare’.” <em>STAT News</em>, September 11, 2023.</li>
  <li>Frimberger, D., et al. “Establishing a Standard Protocol for the Voiding Cystourethrography.” <em>Pediatrics</em>, November 2016.</li>
  <li>Goodman, G.S., et al. “Trauma, memory, and suggestibility in children.” <em>Development and Psychopathology</em>, 1998.</li>
  <li>The Unsilenced Movement advocacy organization and survivor testimonials.</li>
  <li>Personal accounts shared with permission by VCUG survivors.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<div class="author-note">
<p><strong>From Mileena:</strong> Writing this piece made me deeply uncomfortable as I imagined these things happening to children, and it made me furious to investigate this procedure in more detail and discover the extent of systematic failure. The weight of these stories—the institutional negligence, the decades of dismissed trauma—was almost unbearable to hold.</p>

<p>To the survivors who trusted me with their experiences: thank you. Your courage in speaking these truths makes change possible. Your voices will save other children from experiencing what you endured.</p>

<p>If you're a VCUG survivor with a story to share, resources you've found helpful, or simply need someone to witness your truth, <a href="/contact/">I'm here to listen</a>. Sometimes the greatest healing comes from being believed.</p>

<p>For those dealing with medical trauma, <a href="https://www.unsilencedmovement.com/" target="_blank">The Unsilenced Movement</a> offers community and resources specifically for VCUG survivors.</p>

<p>This story isn't over. Change is coming. But it will only come as fast as we demand it.</p>
</div>

<style>
.content-warning-box {
    background: rgba(255, 100, 100, 0.1);
    border: 1px solid #ff6464;
    border-radius: 10px;
    padding: 20px;
    margin-bottom: 40px;
    font-size: 0.95em;
    color: #ffaaaa;
}

.author-note {
    background: linear-gradient(135deg, rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.1), rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.05));
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    border-radius: 0 15px 15px 0;
    padding: 30px;
    margin: 60px 0 40px 0;
    font-style: italic;
}

.author-note p {
    margin-bottom: 15px;
    line-height: 1.8;
}

.author-note p:last-child {
    margin-bottom: 0;
}

.author-note a {
    color: #8a9fff;
    text-decoration: none;
    border-bottom: 1px solid transparent;
    transition: border-color 0.3s ease;
}

.author-note a:hover {
    border-bottom-color: #8a9fff;
}

blockquote {
    background: rgba(40, 40, 50, 0.5);
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    padding: 20px 30px;
    margin: 30px 0;
    font-style: italic;
    color: #ddd;
    border-radius: 0 10px 10px 0;
}

h2 {
    color: #f0f0f0;
    font-weight: 300;
    font-size: 2em;
    margin-top: 60px;
    margin-bottom: 30px;
    letter-spacing: 1px;
}

hr {
    border: none;
    height: 1px;
    background: linear-gradient(to right, transparent, #8a9fff, transparent);
    margin: 60px 0;
}
</style>]]></content><author><name>Mileena Rayne</name></author><category term="Community Stories" /><category term="medical-trauma" /><category term="VCUG" /><category term="childhood-trauma" /><category term="medical-negligence" /><category term="survivor-stories" /><category term="healthcare-reform" /><category term="pediatric-trauma" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In 2023, a pediatric urologist admitted they've never studied the long-term psychological effects of a procedure performed on hundreds of thousands of children annually. Two survivors share what medical research refused to examine for three decades.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/the-procedure-that-shouldnt-exist.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/the-procedure-that-shouldnt-exist.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">When Your First Fight Was Just to Breathe: A Journey Through Unthinkable Trauma</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/30/when-your-first-fight-was-just-to-breathe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When Your First Fight Was Just to Breathe: A Journey Through Unthinkable Trauma" /><published>2025-06-30T08:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-06-30T08:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/30/when-your-first-fight-was-just-to-breathe</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/30/when-your-first-fight-was-just-to-breathe/"><![CDATA[<div class="content-warning-box">
<strong>Content Warning:</strong> This post contains discussions of severe child neglect, abandonment, physical abuse, drug addiction, sexual assault, and medical trauma. Please read with care for yourself.
</div>

<hr />

<p>I never know what to expect when someone sends me their painful story, and each time I’m so honored they entrust me with it. When this story reached me, I felt a sinking feeling in my chest. As a mother of two, I read the unthinkable. It devastates me to understand the lengths of cruelty some will go to against the most vulnerable.</p>

<p>Benji’s message found me on an ordinary day, but there was nothing ordinary about what he trusted me with. At twenty-one years old, he has survived more trauma than most people could comprehend in a lifetime. Yet his words carried something that broke my heart and amazed me simultaneously: the quiet strength of someone who has looked death and abandonment in the face multiple times and chosen, again and again, to stay.</p>

<p>This is his story, shared with his permission, told with profound respect for his courage, and offered to anyone who has ever wondered if survival is enough—because sometimes, survival is everything.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="fighting-for-life-before-you-could-even-fight">Fighting for Life Before You Could Even Fight</h2>

<p>Some people are born into safety, wrapped in love before they take their first breath. Benji entered this world three months early, his tiny body already preparing for a fight that would define his entire existence. The doctors weren’t sure he would make it. His heart required surgery when he was still an infant, his life hanging in the balance while machines did the work his tiny organs couldn’t yet manage.</p>

<p>For months, he lived in the NICU—that liminal space between life and death where parents keep vigil and miracles happen one labored breath at a time. He fought. He survived. He came home.</p>

<p>But home wasn’t the sanctuary it should have been for a child who had already fought so hard just to exist.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Both of my biological parents were deeply addicted to drugs and alcohol. My father was violent. He beat my mother and he beat me too. When he wasn’t hitting us, he’d lock me in a closet for hours in the dark while he and my mother used drugs.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I want to pause here and let that sink in. A child who had already endured heart surgery, who had spent months fighting for life in a hospital, came home to parents who chose drugs over his safety, violence over protection, darkness over love. A tiny person who had already proven his incredible will to live was met with people who seemed determined to extinguish that will.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“That kind of fear and loneliness is something I can still feel in my chest even now.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Trauma lives in the body. It doesn’t matter that Benji was barely old enough to form coherent memories—his nervous system remembers everything. The fear of being locked in darkness. The confusion of being hurt by the people meant to protect him. The bewildering reality of being small and helpless in a world that felt dangerous and unpredictable.</p>

<p>That he can articulate this truth at twenty-one—that he understands how those early experiences still echo in his chest—speaks to a level of self-awareness that most people spend decades trying to achieve.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="when-the-people-who-made-you-unmake-you">When the People Who Made You Unmake You</h2>

<p>When Benji was three, his mother gave birth to his little sister. For a brief moment, I imagine there might have been hope—perhaps the arrival of another child would spark some parental instinct, some recognition of the sacred responsibility they held.</p>

<p>Instead, it marked the beginning of an abandonment so profound it defies comprehension.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Not long after that, she abandoned us. She left me and my baby sister in a park on a day when it was over 105 degrees outside. We were both covered in mosquito bites. We had no food.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>A mother looked at her three-year-old son and infant daughter—children she had carried, birthed, held—and made the conscious decision to leave them in a park in triple-digit heat. No food. No protection. No care for what would happen to them once she walked away.</p>

<p>I keep reading this part of Benji’s story and feeling something inside me break anew each time. Not just because of the abandonment itself, but because of what it reveals about the complete collapse of every instinct that should have protected these children. The biological imperative to care for your offspring, the social contract to protect the vulnerable, the basic human decency to not leave small children to die—all of it simply… gone.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I was never fed properly only given formula even at that age and I was kept in a car seat day and night. Because of that, I couldn’t walk. I needed therapy just to learn how to use my legs.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This detail haunts me. A three-year-old who couldn’t walk because he had been confined to a car seat for so long that his body forgot how to develop normally. Physical therapy just to learn what most children master naturally: another layer of trauma disguised as medical necessity.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I remember my teeth were black because no one ever took care of me. No one brushed them. No one cared.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The specificity of this memory (black teeth as evidence of total neglect) speaks to something I see in many trauma survivors: the way certain details become seared into memory, becoming proof that yes, it really was that bad. That the neglect was real, total, and devastating.</p>

<p>When the police found them in that park, they weren’t just rescuing two children from immediate danger. They were interrupting what would likely have been a death sentence, delivered by the very people who should have died protecting them instead.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-angels-who-appeared-as-grandparents">The Angels Who Appeared as Grandparents</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“When I was around 4 years old my grandparents adopted me and my sister. They saved us. They gave us a real chance at life.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the midst of this catalog of horrors, these words shine like light breaking through darkness. Benji’s grandparents didn’t just take in two traumatized children—they chose to become the parents their own child had failed to be. They looked at a four-year-old who couldn’t walk properly, whose teeth were rotted from neglect, who had been locked in closets and abandoned in parks, and they chose love.</p>

<p>This kind of intervention—older adults stepping in to raise grandchildren when their own children have failed—requires a particular kind of heroism that often goes unrecognized. They were likely already tired, already settled into a phase of life that didn’t include sleepless nights with traumatized children or physical therapy appointments or the complex work of healing bodies and spirits that had been so thoroughly broken.</p>

<p>But they did it anyway. They became the sanctuary that Benji and his sister needed, the proof that not all adults would hurt them, that safety was possible even when it came later than it should have.</p>

<p>The fact that Benji can recognize this gift—that he can see his grandparents as the heroes they are rather than taking their love for granted—speaks to his remarkable capacity for gratitude even after unthinkable betrayal.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="when-trauma-doesnt-stop-at-childhood">When Trauma Doesn’t Stop at Childhood</h2>

<p>For many survivors, there’s a narrative that once you’re rescued, once you’re safe, the hard part is over. But trauma is rarely that neat. The nervous system doesn’t immediately adjust to safety. The body holds onto hypervigilance. And sometimes, despite the best efforts of loving caregivers, more trauma finds you.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I was also SA when I was 14 and again when I was 19 it was terrible as well as having my one dog who meant the world to me die in my arms when I was 20.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The way Benji mentions these additional traumas (sexual assault at fourteen and nineteen, the devastating loss of his beloved dog) speaks to something I recognize in many survivors: the weary acceptance that trauma seems to find them, that they’ve become somehow magnetized to experiences that most people never endure even once.</p>

<p>There’s a particular cruelty in the way trauma can compound. As if surviving the first waves wasn’t enough, as if having already proven your resilience somehow makes you a target for more testing. The loss of his dog (likely one of the few sources of unconditional love and comfort in his life) at twenty years old adds another layer of grief to an already heavy load.</p>

<p>That he can acknowledge these experiences as “terrible” while still maintaining his determination to live shows a level of emotional honesty that many people never achieve. He’s not minimizing his pain or pretending it doesn’t matter. He’s simply stating facts: these things happened, they were awful, and he survived them too.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-body-keeps-score">The Body Keeps Score</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I’m autistic and I live with severe anxiety and POTS (Postural Orthostatic Tachycardia Syndrome). Life hasn’t been easy for me not even from the very beginning.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Benji’s physical and neurological challenges add layers of complexity to his trauma recovery that can’t be overlooked. POTS (a condition where the heart rate increases dramatically when standing up) means his body is already in a constant state of stress response. For someone with extensive trauma history, this creates a perfect storm where psychological and physiological triggers compound each other.</p>

<p>Being autistic in a world that often feels overwhelming and unpredictable must have made his early trauma even more devastating. Research shows that autistic individuals wake up each morning with anxiety levels that non-autistic people typically reach only at the end of their most stressful days. Autistic people live with incredibly high levels of anxiety as their baseline. Add to that the sensory processing differences, difficulty with changes in routine, challenges in reading social cues—all of these neurological realities would have made the chaos and violence of his early years exponentially more traumatic.</p>

<p>Yet he’s learned to navigate all of this. He’s developed coping strategies, found ways to manage his anxiety, learned to work with his body’s limitations rather than against them. The fact that he can articulate these challenges so clearly suggests someone who has done significant work to understand himself and his needs.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-father-who-chose-death-over-change">The Father Who Chose Death Over Change</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“My father died in 2017. He got high and ran into the middle of the road.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s a devastating finality in how Benji describes his biological father’s death. No emotion, no judgment, just facts: addiction continued to rule this man’s life until it killed him. The father who beat his son, who locked him in closets, who failed him in every possible way, chose drugs over recovery, chaos over healing, death over the possibility of change.</p>

<p>I think about the particular kind of grief this must involve—mourning someone who hurt you, processing the death of a person who was never really a father to you. The complicated emotions of knowing that any chance for reconciliation, for apology, for explanation, died with him on that road.</p>

<p>Some part of Benji might have wondered, throughout his teens and early twenties, whether his father would ever get clean, ever reach out, ever acknowledge the damage he had done. That possibility ended in 2017 with a final act of selfishness that prioritized getting high over staying alive.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-mother-who-remains-absent">The Mother Who Remains Absent</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“My biological mother is still alive, but I barely see her. She isn’t really a part of my life anymore. And maybe that’s for the best.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This might be the most emotionally mature statement in Benji’s entire story. The recognition that sometimes the healthiest choice is to accept someone’s continued absence rather than chase after a relationship that has only brought pain. That his mother’s physical survival doesn’t obligate him to maintain emotional connection.</p>

<p>The phrase “and maybe that’s for the best” carries such wisdom. He’s not bitter, not angry—just realistic about the fact that some people are incapable of the love we need from them, and that protecting ourselves sometimes means accepting their limitations and choosing our own peace.</p>

<p>This is the kind of boundary-setting that takes enormous strength and self-awareness. It’s easier to keep hoping, keep trying, keep believing that maybe this time will be different. To accept that it won’t be, to choose your own wellbeing over the fantasy of maternal love—that’s the work of someone who has learned to prioritize their own healing.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-profound-act-of-bearing-witness">The Profound Act of Bearing Witness</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“My story isn’t easy. But it’s mine. I’ve survived things that most people will never understand. And I still struggle every day with the effects of that trauma anxiety, medical challenges, sensory overload but I’m here. I made it.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>These words carry such power, such quiet strength. There’s no self-pity here, no demand for sympathy, no attempt to minimize or dramatize. Just the simple, profound truth: this is what happened, it was awful, and I survived it.</p>

<p>The acknowledgment that he still struggles daily with anxiety, medical challenges, and sensory overload is crucial. Benji isn’t presenting himself as someone who has “overcome” his trauma and now lives happily ever after. He’s honest about the ongoing nature of healing, the way trauma effects ripple through every day, the constant work required to manage symptoms and triggers.</p>

<p>But he’s also clear about something essential: he made it. Against all odds, despite every attempt by genetics, circumstances, and other people to break him, he is still here. Still choosing to wake up each day. Still believing his story matters enough to share it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“To anyone who’s gone through darkness like this: I see you. You’re not alone. And no matter how broken you feel, your story matters. Just like mine does.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is why Benji’s story matters so much. Not just because of what he survived, but because of how he chooses to use that survival. He’s not sharing his trauma for shock value or sympathy. He’s offering it as a lifeline to others who might be drowning in their own darkness, letting them know that someone else has been in the depths and found a way to keep breathing.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="to-benji-who-chose-to-keep-fighting">To Benji, Who Chose to Keep Fighting</h2>

<p>Benji, when you decided to share your story with me, you said you hoped it might help someone feel less alone. I need you to know that you’ve done something far more significant than that. You’ve offered proof that the human spirit can endure the unthinkable and still choose hope. That survival itself is a form of heroism.</p>

<p>Your biological parents failed you in ways that should never happen to any child. They were supposed to protect you, nurture you, keep you safe, and instead they chose addiction, violence, and abandonment. None of that was your fault. Not the abuse, not the neglect, not being locked in closets or left in parks. You were a child who deserved love, and the failure to provide it was entirely theirs.</p>

<p>Your grandparents saw a traumatized four-year-old and chose to become your heroes. They proved that while some people fail catastrophically in their most sacred responsibilities, others rise to meet challenges they never expected to face. They saved you, but you saved yourself too: by choosing to trust them, by doing the hard work of learning to walk and heal and grow despite everything you’d endured.</p>

<p>The sexual assaults you survived as a teenager and young adult—those weren’t your fault either. Trauma survivors often blame themselves for subsequent violations, as if having been hurt before somehow makes them responsible for being hurt again. That’s not how it works. You were victimized by people who chose to cause harm, and their choices had nothing to do with anything you did or didn’t do.</p>

<p>Living with autism, POTS, and severe anxiety while carrying all this trauma history requires a level of strength that most people will never understand. Every day that you manage sensory overload, every day that you work with your body’s limitations, every day that you choose to stay present despite anxiety—these are acts of courage.</p>

<p>You mentioned feeling your childhood fear and loneliness in your chest even now. That’s trauma living in your body, and acknowledging it shows incredible self-awareness. Many people spend decades in denial about how early experiences continue to affect them. You’re twenty-one and already understand something that takes others a lifetime to recognize.</p>

<p>Your choice to maintain distance from your biological mother isn’t cruel or ungrateful. It’s wise. You’ve learned to distinguish between biological relationships and healthy relationships, between obligation and genuine care. That wisdom will protect you and help you build the life you deserve.</p>

<p>The fact that you can articulate your story with such clarity, that you can see your own resilience while acknowledging ongoing struggles, that you can offer hope to others while still processing your own pain: these things speak to a level of emotional intelligence that’s genuinely remarkable.</p>

<p>You said you made it, and you’re right. But it’s more than that. You’ve transformed your survival into something that matters beyond yourself. You’ve turned your pain into a bridge for others. You’ve proven that even when everything and everyone fails you, something indestructible inside you can choose to keep going.</p>

<p>Your story matters because it shows that healing doesn’t require pretending the past didn’t happen. That strength doesn’t mean not struggling. That survival can be its own form of victory, even when it doesn’t look like what movies and books taught us to expect.</p>

<p>Thank you for trusting me with something so profound and painful. Thank you for surviving all of it. Thank you for choosing to share your truth with the hope that it might help someone else. That choice—to transform your pain into purpose—is one of the most beautiful things humans can do.</p>

<hr />

<p>To anyone reading this who recognizes their own experience in Benji’s words: You are not alone in carrying trauma that started before you could even understand what was happening to you. You’re not alone in having parents who failed at the most basic requirements of parenthood. You’re not alone in struggling with ongoing effects of early trauma, in dealing with anxiety and medical challenges that trauma has amplified, in feeling like your nervous system is always on high alert.</p>

<p>Your survival matters. Your healing matters. Your choice to keep going, even when it’s hard, even when you’re tired, even when the trauma effects make everything feel overwhelming—it all matters.</p>

<p>If your family of origin failed you, know that chosen family is real. Grandparents who become parents, friends who become siblings, mentors who become the guidance you needed—these relationships can be every bit as meaningful as biological ones, sometimes more so because they’re based on choice rather than obligation.</p>

<p>Your trauma doesn’t define your worth, but your response to it reveals your strength. The fact that you’re here, reading this, choosing to seek connection and understanding despite everything you’ve been through—that’s profound courage.</p>

<p>Healing isn’t linear. Some days will be harder than others. Some triggers will catch you off guard. Some memories will surface when you least expect them. That’s normal. That’s part of the process. You don’t have to be “over it” to be healing. You don’t have to stop struggling to prove your strength.</p>

<p>There are resources, communities, and people who understand. Therapists who specialize in childhood trauma. Support groups for survivors. Online communities where people share their stories and strategies for healing. You don’t have to figure this out alone.</p>

<p>Most importantly, your story—whatever it contains, however painful it is—matters. Your voice matters. Your experience matters. And you matter, not because of what you’ve survived, but because of who you are: a human being deserving of love, safety, and peace.</p>

<p>Benji found the courage to share his truth. Maybe you’ll find yours too, when you’re ready. And when you do, know that there are people who will believe you, support you, and remind you that survival is sacred, healing is possible, and your life has value beyond what anyone who hurt you could ever understand.</p>

<hr />

<div class="author-note">
<p><strong>From Mileena:</strong> Benji's story arrived in my inbox on what I thought was an ordinary day, but there's nothing ordinary about the courage it takes to share something so raw and painful. His willingness to trust me with his truth, and his hope that it might help someone else feel less alone, represents the kind of generosity that emerges from the deepest wounds—the choice to transform personal pain into collective healing.</p>

<p>Writing this post has left me in awe of the resilience of the human spirit and furious at the systems and people that failed this child so completely. Benji survived medical trauma, severe neglect, abandonment, abuse, and more—yet his words carry not bitterness, but wisdom. Not anger, but hope. That transformation from victim to survivor to someone who offers hope to others is one of the most beautiful things humans can accomplish.</p>

<p>If you're a survivor with a story that needs witnessing, I'm here to listen. Sometimes the greatest healing comes from being believed, from having someone say: "What happened to you was wrong, and you deserved better." <a href="/contact/">Reach out anytime</a>.</p>

<p>If you or someone you know is dealing with childhood trauma, resources like <a href="https://www.childhelp.org/" target="_blank">Childhelp</a> (1-800-422-4453) and <a href="https://www.rainn.org/" target="_blank">RAINN</a> (1-800-656-4673) offer specialized support. For those dealing with autism and related challenges, <a href="https://autisticadvocacy.org/" target="_blank">Autistic Self Advocacy Network</a> provides valuable resources and community.</p>

<p>To Benji: Thank you for trusting me with this. Thank you for surviving. Thank you for choosing to share your truth with the hope that it might light the way for someone else walking through darkness. Your story will help other survivors recognize their own strength, and that matters more than you may ever know.</p>

<p>And to anyone reading this who has survived the unsurvivable: your presence here is proof that love can triumph over abandonment, that healing can emerge from the deepest wounds, that some things inside us are truly unbreakable. Keep going. Your story matters too.</p>
</div>

<style>
.content-warning-box {
    background: rgba(255, 100, 100, 0.1);
    border: 1px solid #ff6464;
    border-radius: 10px;
    padding: 20px;
    margin-bottom: 40px;
    font-size: 0.95em;
    color: #ffaaaa;
}

.author-note {
    background: linear-gradient(135deg, rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.1), rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.05));
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    border-radius: 0 15px 15px 0;
    padding: 30px;
    margin: 60px 0 40px 0;
    font-style: italic;
}

.author-note p {
    margin-bottom: 15px;
    line-height: 1.8;
}

.author-note p:last-child {
    margin-bottom: 0;
}

.author-note a {
    color: #8a9fff;
    text-decoration: none;
    border-bottom: 1px solid transparent;
    transition: border-color 0.3s ease;
}

.author-note a:hover {
    border-bottom-color: #8a9fff;
}

blockquote {
    background: rgba(40, 40, 50, 0.5);
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    padding: 20px 30px;
    margin: 30px 0;
    font-style: italic;
    color: #ddd;
    border-radius: 0 10px 10px 0;
}

h2 {
    color: #f0f0f0;
    font-weight: 300;
    font-size: 2em;
    margin-top: 60px;
    margin-bottom: 30px;
    letter-spacing: 1px;
}

hr {
    border: none;
    height: 1px;
    background: linear-gradient(to right, transparent, #8a9fff, transparent);
    margin: 60px 0;
}
</style>]]></content><author><name>Mileena Rayne</name></author><category term="Community Stories" /><category term="childhood-trauma" /><category term="medical-trauma" /><category term="autism" /><category term="survivor-stories" /><category term="family-abandonment" /><category term="resilience" /><category term="healing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At 21, Benji has survived more trauma than most people could imagine—premature birth, heart surgery, severe neglect, abandonment, abuse, and ongoing medical challenges. His story is proof of the incredible resilience of the human spirit.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/when-your-first-fight-was-just-to-breathe.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/when-your-first-fight-was-just-to-breathe.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Price of Faith: When Doctrine Becomes More Sacred Than Safety</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/28/the-price-of-faith-when-doctrine-becomes-more-sacred-than-safety/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Price of Faith: When Doctrine Becomes More Sacred Than Safety" /><published>2025-06-28T04:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-06-28T04:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/28/the-price-of-faith-when-doctrine-becomes-more-sacred-than-safety</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/28/the-price-of-faith-when-doctrine-becomes-more-sacred-than-safety/"><![CDATA[<div class="content-warning-box">
<strong>Content Warning:</strong> This post contains detailed descriptions of domestic violence, physical abuse, religious trauma, child endangerment, and institutional betrayal. Please read with care for yourself.
</div>

<hr />

<p>Sometimes the most devastating betrayal comes not from strangers, but from the very people who promised that following God meant following them.</p>

<p>When someone reaches out to share their story with me, there’s always a moment where I have to pause and prepare myself for what’s coming. But nothing quite prepared me for Shannon’s story—not because it’s unusual among ex-Jehovah’s Witness accounts, but because it’s heartbreakingly common. The details change, but the pattern remains: a woman trapped between an abusive husband and a religious system that valued her silence more than her safety.</p>

<p>What Shannon shared with me isn’t just a personal story. It’s a damning indictment of how high-control religious organizations systematically fail the most vulnerable among them, how doctrine can become more sacred than human life, and how the very people meant to shepherd the flock become complicit in its destruction.</p>

<p>This is her story, told with her permission, in her honor, and for every woman still trapped in the terrible space between faith and survival.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="born-into-the-truth">Born Into “The Truth”</h2>

<p>Shannon grew up around Jehovah’s Witnesses, though her family’s involvement started on the periphery. Everything changed when her father was diagnosed with lung cancer. Facing mortality, he turned to the faith more seriously, and their family followed suit. Regular meetings, field service, the whole commitment—but even then, Shannon didn’t fully embrace it.</p>

<p>At sixteen, her parents made a decision that would reshape her entire life: they sent her to live with her older sister, who was already a baptized Jehovah’s Witness. This wasn’t just a change of address. This was total immersion into a world where every choice was scrutinized, every relationship filtered through doctrine, every moment measured against an impossible standard of righteousness.</p>

<p>Three meetings a week. Early morning field service. A life where belonging meant conforming, and questioning meant exile.</p>

<p>Despite this intensive indoctrination, Shannon left after high school. She wanted to live her own life. But the organization doesn’t let go easily. Members visited her at work regularly, reminding her how much they “missed” her, how she was “always welcome back.” They understand something crucial about human psychology: the need to belong is one of our deepest drives, and they exploit that need with surgical precision.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I didn’t realize it at the time, but that sense of belonging—of being wanted—was already working its way into my heart.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>After a controlling relationship left her feeling lost and vulnerable, Shannon found herself drawn back to the certainty the organization offered. Structure. Answers. Community. At twenty, she moved to Seattle for a fresh start, continuing her studies in the faith. In 1988, she married. In 1989, both she and her husband were baptized as Jehovah’s Witnesses.</p>

<p>She had convinced herself this was the life she was supposed to live. She had fully embraced it.</p>

<p>What she didn’t know was that her faith—the very thing she thought would save her—was about to become her prison.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-first-hit">The First Hit</h2>

<p>A month after their wedding, it began.</p>

<p>They had gone to bed angry after an argument—something that happens in every marriage. But what happened next was not normal, was not acceptable, was not something that should ever happen between two people who claim to love each other.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Without warning, he sat up, raised his arm, and brought his fist down—full force—onto my thigh. He was 6’5”, I was 5’4”. The impact sent a shockwave of pain through my body, and the next morning, I could barely put weight on my leg.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The bruise was enormous. When he saw her limping the next morning, he cried. He swore it would never happen again. And so the cycle began—violence followed by remorse, promises followed by more violence, hope followed by devastating betrayal.</p>

<p>But this wasn’t just any marriage. This was a marriage within the Jehovah’s Witness organization, where divorce was permitted only for adultery, where wives were taught to be submissive, where “headship” meant unquestioned male authority. Shannon was trapped not just by love or fear, but by doctrine that made leaving spiritually impossible.</p>

<p>The abuse escalated with terrifying calculation:</p>

<ul>
  <li>If she rearranged furniture, she’d wake to find everything restored to his preference</li>
  <li>He would grab the steering wheel while she drove, jerking them toward oncoming traffic to watch her panic</li>
  <li>He destroyed things that were special to her, reminding her that nothing in her life truly belonged to her</li>
  <li>He abused her in front of their children, then told them, “Look at what Mommy is making me do”</li>
</ul>

<p>That last detail breaks something in me every time I read it. A man so twisted that he made his own children witnesses to his violence, then blamed their mother for forcing him to hurt her. Teaching them that love looks like violence, that victims cause their own abuse, that the person being hurt is somehow responsible for the person doing the hurting.</p>

<p>And through it all, Shannon stayed. Because Jehovah hates divorce. Because she had made a covenant—not just to her husband, but to God. Because she believed that if she could just be a better wife, pray harder, submit more completely, somehow the violence would stop.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="seeking-help-from-the-shepherds">Seeking Help from the Shepherds</h2>

<p>When the abuse became impossible to ignore, Shannon did what she had been taught to do: she turned to the elders for guidance. These were supposed to be spiritual shepherds, men appointed by God to care for the flock, protectors of the innocent and defenders of the righteous.</p>

<p>Instead, she found men more concerned with maintaining order than ensuring safety:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Be a better wife.”</em>
<em>“What did you do to provoke him?”</em>
<em>“We’ve had other sisters show up at the Kingdom Hall with black eyes. What makes you think you’re any different?”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Let that last response sink in. They openly admitted that other women had appeared at their place of worship, battered and bruised, seeking help. And their response wasn’t outrage at the violence or immediate action to protect victims. It was to normalize the abuse, to make Shannon feel like just another complaining wife who needed to try harder.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“That last comment shattered me. They admitted openly that I wasn’t the first—that other women had appeared battered and bruised, yet the elders had chosen to send them home, instructing them to try harder.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Shannon left those meetings feeling utterly defeated, convinced that her marriage’s failure was evidence of her own spiritual inadequacy. If she was faithful enough, submissive enough, righteous enough, surely God would fix her husband. Surely her suffering had a purpose.</p>

<p>So she stayed. She prayed harder, submitted more, tried to embody the obedient wife they insisted Jehovah desired. But none of it stopped the abuse. If anything, her increased compliance seemed to embolden her husband’s control.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-night-everything-changed">The Night Everything Changed</h2>

<p>Even pregnancy didn’t stop the violence. At seven months pregnant, he threw her against a wall. Shannon’s mother, visiting during this time, saw the fear in her daughter’s eyes despite Shannon’s silence. She encouraged Shannon to come to Texas for a nephew’s birth.</p>

<p>For one precious month, Shannon was away from him. Safe. Breathing freely. But when he followed her to Texas to bring her back, she complied. The elders reprimanded him—not for nearly killing his pregnant wife, but for driving without a license.</p>

<p>Let’s really think about this for a minute. A man throws his seven-months-pregnant wife against a wall with enough force to potentially kill her and their unborn child. The religious authorities’ primary concern? His traffic violation.</p>

<p>This is the twisted moral calculus of high-control religious groups: rules matter more than people, image matters more than truth, maintaining authority matters more than protecting the vulnerable.</p>

<p>Years of escalating abuse followed. Years of carefully hidden bruises, explained-away injuries, and children growing up thinking violence was normal. Until one night in March, shortly after the memorial service, when everything finally came to a head.</p>

<p>Shannon was temporarily employed with Kelly Services, finding some measure of independence and self-worth in her work. But tensions at home were reaching a breaking point. That evening, she accidentally burned dinner—a simple mistake that any reasonable person would shrug off.</p>

<p>Her husband’s response was anything but reasonable.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“You’re such a piece of shit,” he spat.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>As Shannon retreated to bathe their children—five and three years old—he found fault even there, shoving her aside and mocking her: <em>“You can’t even bathe our kids right.”</em></p>

<p>She went to the bedroom to fold laundry, trying to calm herself with the mundane task. That’s when he stormed in, grabbed a lamp, and smashed it violently on the floor. Then, with the chilling calmness that only true predators possess, he delivered his ultimatum:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“You’re so miserable? Fine. Tomorrow, I’ll get a gun and kill you, me, and the kids.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>He punctuated this threat by punching the mirror, sending glass shards flying dangerously close to their three-year-old son who was standing in the closet.</p>

<p>Something inside Shannon snapped. Not into pieces, but into clarity. Without hesitation, she grabbed her children and fled. When her daughter cried about not having shoes, Shannon reassured her gently: <em>“It’s okay, baby.”</em></p>

<p>But where do you go when you have no money, no support system, and a religious community that has repeatedly told you that your suffering is your own fault?</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="when-the-shepherds-become-wolves">When the Shepherds Become Wolves</h2>

<p>Shannon drove to the home of an elder—someone she considered a friend, someone who was supposed to offer guidance and compassion in moments of crisis. Shaking, she stood at his door with her children clinging to her, explaining the terrifying threats, the shattered mirror, their desperate escape.</p>

<p>She expected help. Empathy. At the very least, support for a mother protecting her children from credible death threats.</p>

<p>Instead, he folded his arms and asked with cold calculation: <em>“Where are you going to go?”</em></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“The simplicity of his question felt like a physical blow. I had no answer. No money for a hotel, no family nearby, nowhere safe to retreat. In that devastating moment, I realized he wouldn’t help. He wouldn’t call another congregation member or offer guidance. He certainly wouldn’t reassure me I’d done the right thing.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Think about this moment. A terrified mother, fleeing with her small children from a man who had just threatened to murder them all, stands on the doorstep of a religious leader—someone she trusted, someone she believed represented God’s compassion—and is met with a question designed to send her back to her would-be killer.</p>

<p>He knew she had nowhere to go. That was precisely why he asked. He was counting on her desperation to force her back into the situation she had just escaped. This wasn’t pastoral care. It was calculated manipulation designed to preserve the facade of a happy Jehovah’s Witness marriage.</p>

<p>Shannon was forced to call her husband’s family, begging for one night’s shelter. Her brother-in-law hesitated, knowing about the violence and not wanting trouble. Thankfully, his wife intervened, insisting they take her in.</p>

<p>The next morning brought a phone call that would reveal just how deep the knowledge of abuse ran within the family. Her mother-in-law called and asked, <em>“What happened?”</em></p>

<p>When Shannon told her everything—the threats, the violence, the fear—her mother-in-law sighed deeply and said something chilling: <em>“I had hoped this wouldn’t happen.”</em></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“She knew. She had always known. Because she had lived it too—abuse at the hands of her own husband. And like me, she stayed until the day she couldn’t take it anymore, ending her life to escape his control.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>For the next few weeks, Shannon was homeless with two young children, bouncing from couch to couch, surviving on the temporary kindness of others. Even after finding work, the pressure from well-meaning friends mounted:</p>

<p><em>“He’s such a great guy.”</em>
<em>“Work on your marriage.”</em>
<em>“Think about how hard this is for him.”</em></p>

<p>These weren’t strangers making these comments. These were people who knew her, who had seen glimpses of what she endured, who still chose to prioritize the comfort of her abuser over her safety. This is how abuse is perpetuated within tight-knit communities: through the collective decision to look away, to make excuses, to place the burden of “keeping the family together” on the person being destroyed by it.</p>

<p>Desperation and isolation led Shannon to make a decision she would later regret: she let him move back in. He promised everything would change. He promised he couldn’t live without her and the children. He invoked God, promising that Jehovah would help him become the husband she deserved.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I believed him. Years of control had convinced me I couldn’t survive alone. I escaped—only to be pulled back in.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="when-the-system-betrays-its-own">When the System Betrays Its Own</h2>

<p>Nothing got better. If anything, the violence escalated as her husband punished her for the humiliation of her brief escape. The control tightened like a noose, and Shannon found herself more isolated than ever.</p>

<p>In desperation, she returned to the elders one final time, pleading for permission to leave, hoping they would finally prioritize her life over their doctrine. Instead, they delivered a blow that would shatter her faith forever:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“You’re twisting scriptures to suit your situation.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>They denied her abuse was real. They refused to acknowledge what they had seen with their own eyes. They prioritized doctrine over her survival, maintaining their interpretation of scripture over protecting a woman whose life was in danger.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“That moment changed me. They weren’t Jehovah’s representatives—they were just men protecting their rules, not me. For the first time, I knew clearly: I’d have to save myself.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is the moment of recognition that every survivor of religious abuse eventually faces: the realization that the people claiming to represent God’s love are more interested in protecting their authority than practicing actual compassion. That the system designed to nurture your soul is systematically destroying your spirit.</p>

<p>Shannon’s faith didn’t just crack in that moment—it underwent a fundamental transformation. She stopped looking to fallible men for salvation and started trusting her own moral compass. She stopped confusing obedience with righteousness and started understanding that sometimes the most godly thing you can do is refuse to submit to ungodly treatment.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-day-justice-intervened">The Day Justice Intervened</h2>

<p>A few months later, as Shannon was slowly rebuilding some stability in her life, she returned home to find an empty house. The phone rang. It was the same elder who had previously refused to help her.</p>

<p><em>“Your husband’s in jail. Your children are with the neighbor.”</em></p>

<p>Confusion turned to shocking revelation: unbeknownst to Shannon, someone had reported the domestic violence. When given a choice by the judge between anger management or jail, her husband made a decision that revealed everything about his character—he arrogantly chose jail. Three years.</p>

<p>Instead of relief, Shannon felt panic. Years of trauma bonding, of being told she was nothing without him, of having her reality systematically dismantled, had left her psychologically dependent on her abuser. At 2 AM, she called her boss, unable to face work.</p>

<p>Her boss’s response changed everything:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“What happened?” she asked gently, then insisted firmly, “This won’t happen again. Call EAP now.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>For the first time in her marriage, someone pointed Shannon toward real help—and she took it. Employee Assistance Program counseling would become the first step in a journey toward actual healing, toward professional support that didn’t come with religious conditions or victim-blaming theology.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="finally-getting-real-help">Finally Getting Real Help</h2>

<p>At her first counseling session, Shannon felt broken and lost. After hearing her story, the counselor leaned forward with validation that had been withheld for years:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Shannon, this is domestic violence.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Five simple words that shattered years of denial and gaslighting. This wasn’t her fault. This wasn’t marital trouble that could be fixed with more prayer and submission. This was a pattern of abuse with a name, with research behind it, with professional support available.</p>

<p>The counselor referred her to Pete, a domestic violence specialist whose kindness would become a turning point in Shannon’s life. For the first time, someone saw her pain clearly and validated her experience without conditions. Slowly, she began to see herself again—not as a failed wife, but as a survivor.</p>

<p>But even with her husband incarcerated, Shannon wasn’t truly free. Jehovah’s Witness doctrine allowed divorce only for adultery—not abuse. If she remained faithful to their teachings, she was expected to wait for him, to forgive him, to welcome him back when his sentence ended.</p>

<p>She saw only one way out: commit adultery herself, knowing it would result in disfellowshipping but would also grant her the divorce she desperately needed.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Not about love or desire, but survival. I confessed, knowing disfellowshipping would free me from their control. And it worked.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-price-of-freedom">The Price of Freedom</h2>

<p>Disfellowshipping in the Jehovah’s Witness organization means total social death. Family members, friends, everyone you’ve ever known within the community—they’re all required to shun you completely. No phone calls, no letters, no acknowledgment of your existence. You become a ghost among the living.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Disfellowshipping meant total abandonment. Family, friends—everyone would shun me completely. Yet, amid profound loss, I felt relief. I’d lost everything I’d been taught to value but reclaimed something infinitely more important: myself.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The irony is staggering: a violent man who had threatened to murder his wife and children faced no consequences from the organization. But a woman who strategically created her own path to freedom was punished with complete exile.</p>

<p>In their upside-down moral universe:</p>
<ul>
  <li>A violent man: forgivable</li>
  <li>A woman fighting to survive: unforgivable</li>
</ul>

<p>Shannon didn’t attend the meeting where her disfellowshipping was announced. She already knew what was coming. But the betrayal still stung deeply. Her abuser remained in good standing while she was branded as the transgressor.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“In protecting the institution over victims, the elders showed their true priorities.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hoping to prevent other women from suffering what she had endured, Shannon wrote to Bethel (the Jehovah’s Witness headquarters), urging better education for elders about domestic violence. Their response was as predictable as it was crushing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“You’re just angry about being disfellowshipped and seeking revenge.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Even her attempt to protect future victims was dismissed as bitter vindictiveness. They had no interest in examining their failures, no willingness to acknowledge that their system had nearly cost a woman and her children their lives.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-long-road-to-healing">The Long Road to Healing</h2>

<p>Shannon moved forward, found love again, and felt safe for the first time in years. But her abuser, still supported by the elders, remained protected within the community. She faced ongoing harassment while he enjoyed continued fellowship.</p>

<p>When Pete, her domestic violence counselor, died unexpectedly, grief pulled Shannon back toward the organization. Seeking reinstatement, she endured harsh interrogations from elders who focused on her past “sins” rather than the trauma that had driven them. Though they eventually reinstated her, something within her had irreparably broken.</p>

<p>Returning to the Kingdom Hall triggered severe PTSD. She was assigned to the same congregation where her abuse had occurred, surrounded by painful reminders. She faced judgment for her appearance, labeled rebellious for a hairstyle that reflected her hard-won autonomy.</p>

<p>When her stepson was murdered, the congregation that claimed to be her spiritual family offered no compassion. The contrast between their conditional love and the unconditional support she found elsewhere became impossible to ignore.</p>

<p>Shannon and her husband began researching the organization’s history, uncovering lies, cover-ups, and systematic cruelty that extended far beyond her personal experience. They discovered they weren’t isolated victims but part of a pattern of institutional betrayal that spanned decades.</p>

<p>Finally, they made the decision that would truly set them free: they chose not to officially disassociate, denying the organization any power over them whatsoever.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“They no longer had power over us. We were free.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="to-shannon-and-to-everyone-still-trapped">To Shannon, and to Everyone Still Trapped</h2>

<p>Shannon’s story is not an anomaly. It’s a blueprint—a detailed map of how high-control religious organizations systematically fail domestic violence victims while protecting their abusers. How they use doctrine as a weapon against the vulnerable while hiding their failures behind claims of divine authority.</p>

<p>But it’s also a story of impossible courage. Of a woman who, when every system that should have protected her instead betrayed her, found the strength to protect herself. Who chose her children’s safety over religious approval. Who endured complete social exile rather than submit to a system that valued her silence more than her life.</p>

<p>To Shannon: Your story matters because it exposes truths that powerful institutions work hard to hide. You survived not just physical abuse, but systematic psychological manipulation designed to make you complicit in your own destruction. You broke cycles that had trapped generations before you. You chose truth over comfort, safety over approval, authenticity over acceptance.</p>

<p>Your ex-husband faced no consequences for years of terror, but you were punished for seeking freedom. That injustice is not on you—it’s on a system so morally bankrupt that it protects predators while exiling their victims.</p>

<p>You deserve every ounce of peace you’ve found. You deserve love that never comes with violence. You deserve a life where your voice matters, where your safety is non-negotiable, where you don’t have to hide bruises or explain away your fear.</p>

<p>To everyone still trapped in situations like Shannon’s: Your abuse is real, and it’s not your fault. No amount of prayer, submission, or faith will fix someone who chooses violence. You don’t have to earn safety through perfect behavior. You don’t have to endure abuse to prove your righteousness.</p>

<p>The people telling you to stay, to submit, to try harder—they’re not the ones living with your fear. They’re not the ones hiding bruises or walking on eggshells or shielding children from violence. You are the expert on your own experience, and if that experience tells you you’re in danger, trust it.</p>

<p>There is life beyond the walls that contain you. There are communities that won’t require you to choose between safety and belonging. There are people who will believe you, support you, and love you without conditions.</p>

<p>Your faith—real faith, not the manipulated version used to control you—doesn’t require you to submit to abuse. Your God, if you believe in one, doesn’t want you to suffer for someone else’s sins. Your children deserve to see what healthy love looks like, not learn that violence is normal.</p>

<p>When you’re ready—and only you can decide when that is—you won’t walk alone. There are professionals like Pete who understand domestic violence. There are support groups full of survivors who will recognize your story. There are resources, legal protections, and safe houses designed to help you transition to freedom.</p>

<p>Most importantly, there are parts of yourself that abuse has never touched—strength, wisdom, intuition, love—waiting to flourish once you’re finally safe enough to tend them.</p>

<p>Shannon found her way out. So can you.</p>

<p>You are worth saving. You always were.</p>

<hr />

<p>To those reading this who have never experienced religious abuse or domestic violence: Shannon’s story isn’t entertainment or inspiration. It’s an indictment of systems many people continue to trust, defend, and support. When institutions prioritize their reputation over people’s safety, when leaders choose doctrine over compassion, when communities punish victims while protecting abusers, we all become complicit through our silence.</p>

<p>If you’re part of a religious community, ask hard questions about how domestic violence is handled. Push for training, for policies that protect victims, for accountability that extends to spiritual leaders. Refuse to accept “submit more” as an answer to abuse reports.</p>

<p>If you’re a friend or family member of someone in an abusive situation, don’t pressure them to stay for religious reasons. Don’t minimize their fear or tell them that prayer will fix their abuser. Believe them. Support them. Help them create a safety plan for when they’re ready to leave.</p>

<p>And if you’re in a position of authority—whether religious, legal, or social—remember that sometimes the most sacred thing you can do is help someone escape the system that’s destroying them, even if that system is your own.</p>

<p>Shannon’s courage in leaving, in healing, and in sharing her story creates space for others to recognize their own experiences and seek their own freedom. That’s what real faith looks like: choosing love over fear, truth over comfort, healing over harm.</p>

<p>Her voice joins the growing chorus of survivors who refuse to let their suffering be invisible, who transform their pain into wisdom, who use their freedom to light the way for others still trapped in darkness.</p>

<p>That’s the kind of faith that actually saves people.</p>

<hr />

<div class="author-note">
<p><strong>From Mileena:</strong> Shannon's story reached me at a time when I'm constantly asking why certain stories find their way to me. I think it's because these experiences—religious trauma, domestic violence, systematic betrayal by those meant to protect us—they're not isolated incidents. They're patterns that reveal something broken in systems many people still trust blindly.</p>

<p>Writing Shannon's story has left me both heartbroken and furious. Heartbroken for every woman who has stood where she stood, seeking help from people who chose doctrine over human life. Furious at systems that claim divine authority while consistently failing the most vulnerable among them.</p>

<p>If you're a survivor with a story that needs witnessing, I'm here to listen. Your voice matters. Your truth matters. And sometimes the greatest healing comes from being believed, from having someone say: "What happened to you was wrong, and you deserved better." <a href="/contact/">Reach out anytime</a>.</p>

<p>If you or someone you know is experiencing domestic violence, please reach out to the <a href="https://www.thehotline.org/" target="_blank">National Domestic Violence Hotline</a> at 1-800-799-7233. For those dealing with religious trauma specifically, resources like <a href="https://recoveringfromreligion.org/" target="_blank">Recovering from Religion</a> offer specialized support.</p>

<p>And to Shannon, wherever you are: thank you for trusting me with this. Thank you for surviving. Thank you for choosing freedom over fear, truth over silence, your children's safety over religious approval. Your story will help other women recognize their own strength, and that matters more than you may ever know.</p>

<p>Shannon also shares her journey and insights on her YouTube channel <a href="https://youtube.com/@DeservinglyYou" target="_blank">@DeservinglyYou</a>, where she continues to offer support and encouragement to other survivors finding their way to freedom.</p>
</div>

<style>
.content-warning-box {
    background: rgba(255, 100, 100, 0.1);
    border: 1px solid #ff6464;
    border-radius: 10px;
    padding: 20px;
    margin-bottom: 40px;
    font-size: 0.95em;
    color: #ffaaaa;
}

.author-note {
    background: linear-gradient(135deg, rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.1), rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.05));
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    border-radius: 0 15px 15px 0;
    padding: 30px;
    margin: 60px 0 40px 0;
    font-style: italic;
}

.author-note p {
    margin-bottom: 15px;
    line-height: 1.8;
}

.author-note p:last-child {
    margin-bottom: 0;
}

.author-note a {
    color: #8a9fff;
    text-decoration: none;
    border-bottom: 1px solid transparent;
    transition: border-color 0.3s ease;
}

.author-note a:hover {
    border-bottom-color: #8a9fff;
}

blockquote {
    background: rgba(40, 40, 50, 0.5);
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    padding: 20px 30px;
    margin: 30px 0;
    font-style: italic;
    color: #ddd;
    border-radius: 0 10px 10px 0;
}

h2 {
    color: #f0f0f0;
    font-weight: 300;
    font-size: 2em;
    margin-top: 60px;
    margin-bottom: 30px;
    letter-spacing: 1px;
}

hr {
    border: none;
    height: 1px;
    background: linear-gradient(to right, transparent, #8a9fff, transparent);
    margin: 60px 0;
}
</style>]]></content><author><name>Mileena Rayne</name></author><category term="Community Stories" /><category term="jehovahs-witness" /><category term="domestic-violence" /><category term="religious-trauma" /><category term="elder-abuse" /><category term="survivor-stories" /><category term="spiritual-abuse" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A survivor shares her harrowing journey through domestic violence within the Jehovah's Witness organization—how she was failed by elders, abandoned by doctrine, and ultimately saved herself when no one else would.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/default-post-image.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/default-post-image.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">When Family Becomes the Enemy: A Survivor’s 32-Year Journey to Freedom from Cult Abuse</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/24/when-family-becomes-the-enemy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When Family Becomes the Enemy: A Survivor’s 32-Year Journey to Freedom from Cult Abuse" /><published>2025-06-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-06-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/24/when-family-becomes-the-enemy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/24/when-family-becomes-the-enemy/"><![CDATA[<div class="content-warning-box">
<strong>Content Warning:</strong> This post contains detailed descriptions of childhood physical abuse, domestic violence, religious trauma, and family estrangement. Please read with care for yourself.
</div>

<hr />

<p>Sometimes a story arrives that makes you understand why some people spend decades learning to trust their own perception of reality. Why it takes thirty-two years to finally close a door that should never have been opened in the first place.</p>

<p>When I asked for stories from the ex-JW community, this person responded with something that stirred a deep, familiar ache I’m learning to recognize. Not just because of what they survived, but because of how heartbreakingly common it’s become to hear stories of children utterly failed by the very people who should have been their sanctuary. There’s a profound sadness in realizing how predictable these patterns have become—how often I find myself reading about parents, congregations, and belief systems that claim to cherish family above all else, yet consistently abandon the most vulnerable when protecting them becomes inconvenient.</p>

<p>Their story came with a legend: code names for the people who shaped their trauma: SPERM for the biological father, HEART ATTACK for the mother, NAME for the adoptive father who became their primary abuser. Even in telling their story, they needed distance from the people who caused such devastation.</p>

<p>There’s something both heartbreaking and brilliant about this protective instinct—this ability to create emotional barriers when physical ones weren’t possible. It speaks to the kind of survival intelligence that children develop when the world around them becomes a battlefield, and they must become both soldier and strategist to endure another day.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="born-into-chaos">Born Into Chaos</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Born into the cult. SPERM (biological father) and HEART ATTACK (mother) married and divorced twice in 3 years.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The foundation of this person’s life was instability wrapped in religious certainty—a contradiction that would shape every relationship they’d ever attempt to build. Their biological father had converted to become a Jehovah’s Witness at age eight, and as a teenager, he brought others into the organization, including the woman who would become this child’s mother and the man who would become their adoptive father and primary abuser.</p>

<p>I can’t help but think about the tragic irony of the biological father’s fate—how he spread his newfound faith like seeds, never knowing he was planting the very system that would eventually exile him and terrorize his child. There’s a cruel irony in the way religious conversion can become both salvation and damnation, depending on which side of the righteousness you find yourself standing.</p>

<p>By age three, the marriage had collapsed twice, the biological father was disfellowshipped, and the adoptive father had married their mother. The adoption papers were signed shortly after a half-sister was born, legally binding this child to a man who would spend the next thirteen years terrorizing them.</p>

<p>But the trauma began even earlier than that.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“First childhood memory is HEART ATTACK (mother) waking NAME (adoptive father) up from bedtime by touching his shoulder. He jumped out of bed grabbed her by the throat grabbed knife off desk and was in the middle of downward thrust when I screamed.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I read this line over and over, each time feeling something break inside me a little more. Their first memory—the earliest thing their developing mind deemed important enough to hold onto—was watching their adoptive father nearly murder their mother. A child so young they couldn’t yet form complete sentences was already learning that home was not safe, that the adults meant to protect them were capable of lethal violence, and that sometimes a scream was the only thing standing between life and death.</p>

<p>The adoptive father walked out that day and didn’t return until evening. No explanation. No accountability. Just a child left to process what they had witnessed, knowing that tomorrow they would still be trapped in the same house with the same danger. How do you explain to a toddler that what they saw was attempted murder? How do you sleep in a house where love and violence dance so closely together they become indistinguishable?</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-darth-vader-years">The Darth Vader Years</h2>

<p>In 1978, the family moved to property owned by the biological father’s family. This created a unique form of psychological torture: living surrounded by reminders of a father they barely knew, in a religious community that required them to view that father as spiritually dead.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“SPERM (biological father) was compared to being Darth Vader and me Luke Skywalker most of my preadolescent and adolescent years by both NAME (adoptive father) and HEART ATTACK (mother) but also my blood relatives and the cult members.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The cruelty of this metaphor takes my breath away. A child being told their biological father is like Darth Vader: the ultimate cinematic representation of a father who chose darkness over his child. But in this twisted version, the “good guys” weren’t the rebels fighting the Empire. They were the community that had driven the father out, the adoptive father who brought violence into their home, the mother who allowed it to continue.</p>

<p>The adults in this child’s life turned their pain into a story—but not the kind of story that heals. Instead, they created a narrative where the child was trapped between a fallen father and righteous guardians, never acknowledging that their “righteousness” was built on brutality.</p>

<p>The first time they remember seeing their biological father, he brought a toy car. A simple gift that triggered a committee meeting with three elders and a visiting circuit overseer to determine whether accepting it was spiritually appropriate. A child’s natural desire to connect with their father became a matter requiring religious tribunal.</p>

<p>I imagine that little toy car sitting there while grown men debated whether love could be accepted from the “wrong” source. How a gift born from paternal affection was dissected like evidence in a trial where the verdict was predetermined. This is the insidious nature of high-control groups: they poison even the most innocent human connections, turning a toy car into evidence of spiritual weakness, a father’s love into a test of loyalty.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="learning-to-survive">Learning to Survive</h2>

<p>When the family moved back in 1984 or 1985, the physical abuse from the adoptive father escalated.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Physically abuse got worse for the next 2 years. Covered up bruises and injuries from school officials but also discovered ability to shut off sensation of pain. Broken teeth finger sprains.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This passage haunts me in ways I struggle to articulate. The matter-of-fact way they describe learning to dissociate from physical pain, as if developing this survival mechanism was as natural as learning to ride a bike. Covering bruises so the outside world wouldn’t know. Developing the ability to “shut off sensation”—a psychological defense that probably saved their life but came at the cost of learning to disconnect from their own body.</p>

<p>I think about that child, standing in school bathrooms, carefully arranging clothing to hide evidence of what home really looked like. Learning to lie with the kind of sophistication that should never be required of a seven-year-old. Broken teeth. Finger sprains. Injuries that required explanation to school officials who were supposed to be mandated reporters but either didn’t see or didn’t act.</p>

<p>The system failed this child at every level—family, community, school, religion. Everyone who should have intervened instead turned away, leaving a small person to navigate horrors that would break most adults.</p>

<p>At sixteen, something shifted.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“At 16 I threatened NAME (adoptive father) with death if I saw him ever again physically abuse any of my siblings.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This moment represents something profound—not just teenage rebellion, but the emergence of a protector from within a victim. A trauma survivor recognizing that if they didn’t stand up, their younger siblings would continue to suffer what they had endured. They made themselves a shield, knowing it would likely cost them everything, because watching more children suffer what they had suffered was unbearable.</p>

<p>The courage required for this act hits me hard. To face down the man who had terrorized you for thirteen years and say “no more”—not for yourself, but for others who couldn’t yet find their voice.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-price-of-choosing-freedom">The Price of Choosing Freedom</h2>

<p>In 1993, they joined the Navy, a decision that led to their disfellowshipping. Military service was forbidden, but for someone who had grown up under authoritarian control, perhaps the structure of military life felt like freedom compared to the psychological prison of their childhood.</p>

<p>I wonder if they found peace in following orders from people who weren’t trying to break them. If there was relief in a hierarchy that was honest about being a hierarchy, instead of calling itself love while wielding power like a weapon.</p>

<p>When their mother had her first heart attack, they went to the hospital. What happened next encapsulates the devastating reality of conditional love within high-control groups:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Upon seeing me at the doorway she said ‘What the fuck are you doing here’. I left put hole in stairwell concrete block wall.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>A child rushes to their mother’s hospital bedside—because despite everything, love doesn’t die easily—and instead of comfort or connection, they’re met with rejection so harsh it drives them to put their fist through concrete. The rawness of that moment, the way concern transforms into rage when met with cruelty, tells the story of every trauma survivor who keeps hoping the people who hurt them will somehow become the people who heal them.</p>

<p>Twelve years later, at a funeral for a family member who wasn’t in the organization, the scene repeated:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“She repeated the same statement 12 years later at her father’s funeral that wasn’t a cult member.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Twice. Their mother looked at them—a child she had carried, raised, should have protected—and made them feel like their existence was an offense. That level of rejection doesn’t just hurt. It rewrites your understanding of your own worth, your right to exist, your place in the world.</p>

<p>The consistency of her rejection became its own form of message: You are not wanted. You do not belong. Your presence is offensive.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-32-year-journey-to-freedom">The 32-Year Journey to Freedom</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I have no connection or contact with any of them anymore took me 32 years to finally close the door to contact.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Thirty-two years. Let that sink in. Three decades of trying to maintain some thread of connection to people who had made their childhood a war zone. Three decades of hoping, trying, being hurt again and again before finally accepting that some doors need to be closed permanently.</p>

<p>There’s something both tragic and beautiful about the human capacity to keep reaching toward love, even when all evidence suggests it will never be returned. For thirty-two years, this person carried hope like a candle in a hurricane, protecting that small flame of possibility that maybe, someday, their family would choose them.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Went through every form of emotional mental and physical stress. Live with it daily but after cutting them out recently it seems to be easier to think of them as dead.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This line breaks me open every time I read it. Not because it’s harsh, but because it represents the kind of grief that has no name—mourning people who are still alive but were never really there for you. When people prove repeatedly that contact with them causes trauma, when they cannot or will not change, sometimes the only healing path is to grieve them as if they’ve died.</p>

<p>Because in a very real way, the people who might have loved you, who should have loved you, never actually existed. You’re not mourning who they were—you’re mourning who they could have been, should have been, who you needed them to be.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-strength-that-remains">The Strength That Remains</h2>

<p>What strikes me most about this story is not the catalog of horrors this person endured—though they are staggering—but the profound resilience that carried them through each moment of choice. The decision to protect their siblings. The decision to show care when their mother had a medical emergency, even knowing they’d likely have it thrown back in their face. The decision to keep trying for thirty-two years. And finally, the decision to stop trying and choose themselves.</p>

<p>Each of these choices required a different kind of courage. The courage to fight. The courage to love despite being unloved. The courage to hope despite repeated disappointment. And ultimately, the courage to let go. They kept a door open for three decades, waiting for people who would never walk through it.</p>

<p>This isn’t failure. This is wisdom earned through unimaginable pain. This is someone who spent thirty-two years learning the difference between love and loyalty, between family and biology, between hope and delusion.</p>

<hr />

<p>To the person who shared this story: Your journey amazes me. Not just what you survived, but how you survived it. How you protected others when no one protected you. How you kept trying when trying only brought pain. How you finally learned to protect yourself when no one else would.</p>

<p>Your childhood should have been filled with safety and love. Your teenage years should have been about discovering who you were, not defending who you had a right to be. Your early adulthood should have been about building your own life, not healing from the destruction of your earliest years.</p>

<p>None of this should have happened to you. And yet, you’re here. You survived. You learned to distinguish between the people who claimed to love you and the people who actually did. You spent thirty-two years trying to believe in a version of family that didn’t exist, and then you found the strength to stop trying.</p>

<p>Your story matters because it shows that healing doesn’t always look like reconciliation. Sometimes healing looks like finally admitting that some people aren’t capable of the love you need, and choosing to find that love elsewhere. Sometimes healing means understanding that you can’t save people who don’t want to be saved—including family members.</p>

<p>Thank you for trusting me with something so profound and painful. Thank you for surviving all of it. Thank you for choosing yourself when no one else would.</p>

<hr />

<p>To anyone reading this who sees their own story reflected here: You are not alone in this particular kind of grief. The grief of losing family members who are still alive. The grief of accepting that the love you needed was never available from the people who should have provided it. The grief of choosing your own healing over maintaining relationships that only bring harm.</p>

<p>Family dysfunction, religious trauma, childhood abuse—these experiences can make you feel like you’re living in a different reality from everyone else. Like your pain is too complicated, too ugly, too much to share. But stories like this one prove that survival is possible. That healing is possible. That choosing yourself over toxic loyalty isn’t selfish—it’s necessary.</p>

<p>If you’re still trapped, know that escape is possible. If you’ve escaped but are still trying to maintain connections that hurt you, know that it’s okay to close those doors. If you’ve already closed them and are grieving, know that your grief is real and valid and necessary.</p>

<p>Sometimes the most radical act of self-preservation is admitting that the people who were supposed to protect you became the ones you needed protection from. And sometimes the greatest act of love is loving yourself enough to walk away from people who refuse to see your worth.</p>

<p>You are not responsible for healing people who hurt you. You are not obligated to keep doors open for people who repeatedly choose to bring harm into your life. You are allowed to choose peace over chaos, healing over hope, yourself over anyone who refuses to see your value.</p>

<p>Your story matters. Your healing matters. Your choice to survive, to thrive, to finally put yourself first—it all matters.</p>

<hr />

<div class="author-note">
<p><strong>From Mileena:</strong> Stories like this remind me why I create space for voices that have been silenced, experiences that have been invalidated, truths that make people uncomfortable. This person's journey—from terrorized child to someone who finally chose their own peace—represents a kind of healing that doesn't fit into neat narratives but is profoundly real.</p>

<p>If you have a story that needs to be heard, a truth that needs witnessing, I'm here to listen. Sometimes the greatest healing comes from simply being believed, from having someone say: "What happened to you was wrong, and you deserve better." <a href="/contact/">Reach out anytime</a>.</p>

<p>And to those still trapped in situations like this: You deserve safety. You deserve love that doesn't come with conditions or violence. You deserve peace. The world outside whatever prison you're in is scary, yes, but it's also full of people who will believe you, support you, and love you for exactly who you are—without requiring you to hide bruises or explain away your pain.</p>

<p>You are worth fighting for. Even when—especially when—the people who should have fought for you didn't.</p>
</div>

<style>
.content-warning-box {
    background: rgba(255, 100, 100, 0.1);
    border: 1px solid #ff6464;
    border-radius: 10px;
    padding: 20px;
    margin-bottom: 40px;
    font-size: 0.95em;
    color: #ffaaaa;
}

.author-note {
    background: linear-gradient(135deg, rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.1), rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.05));
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    border-radius: 0 15px 15px 0;
    padding: 30px;
    margin: 60px 0 40px 0;
    font-style: italic;
}

.author-note p {
    margin-bottom: 15px;
    line-height: 1.8;
}

.author-note p:last-child {
    margin-bottom: 0;
}

blockquote {
    background: rgba(40, 40, 50, 0.5);
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    padding: 20px 30px;
    margin: 30px 0;
    font-style: italic;
    color: #ddd;
    border-radius: 0 10px 10px 0;
}

h2 {
    color: #f0f0f0;
    font-weight: 300;
    font-size: 2em;
    margin-top: 60px;
    margin-bottom: 30px;
    letter-spacing: 1px;
}

hr {
    border: none;
    height: 1px;
    background: linear-gradient(to right, transparent, #8a9fff, transparent);
    margin: 60px 0;
}
</style>]]></content><author><name>Mileena Rayne</name></author><category term="Community Stories" /><category term="jehovahs-witness" /><category term="childhood-abuse" /><category term="family-trauma" /><category term="domestic-violence" /><category term="cult-recovery" /><category term="survivor-stories" /><category term="religious-trauma" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A survivor shares their harrowing journey through childhood abuse within the Jehovah's Witness organization, domestic violence, and the 32-year path to finally cutting toxic family ties.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/when-family-becomes-the-enemy.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/when-family-becomes-the-enemy.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">When Everything You Knew Was a Lie: One Survivor’s Journey from Jehovah’s Witnesses to Searching the Stars for Truth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/22/when-everything-you-knew-was-a-lie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When Everything You Knew Was a Lie: One Survivor’s Journey from Jehovah’s Witnesses to Searching the Stars for Truth" /><published>2025-06-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-06-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/22/when-everything-you-knew-was-a-lie</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/22/when-everything-you-knew-was-a-lie/"><![CDATA[<div class="video-notice-box">
<strong>Video Version Available:</strong> You can also watch this story as a video at the bottom of this post.
</div>

<div class="content-warning-box">
<strong>Content Warning:</strong> This post contains discussions of child sexual abuse, suicide, religious trauma, and family estrangement. Please read with care for yourself.
</div>

<hr />

<p>Sometimes a story arrives in your inbox that makes you stop everything. That makes you close your laptop and sit in silence because the weight of someone’s truth deserves that kind of reverence.</p>

<p>When I put out my call for stories, when I promised that every voice would be heard, that every experience mattered, I thought I knew what might come back. I was wrong. This person, this fellow traveler who left everything behind for truth, handed me their story like a broken bird. Carefully. Trusting me not to drop it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“You want an ex-Jehovah’s Witness story?”</em> they asked.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yes. Always yes. Because these stories matter. Because in the spaces between our stories, healing finds room to breathe.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="when-paradise-hides-hell">When Paradise Hides Hell</h2>

<p>They were born into it, like I was. We sat in the same Kingdom Halls, sang the same songs, believed in the same paradise. But behind the identical walls of our congregations, two children were living in completely different worlds.</p>

<p>What happened to them—what their father did, what their mother allowed, what the elders ignored—it breaks something in me to know it was happening while we were all singing about God’s love. While we were all pretending to be the happiest people on earth.</p>

<p>Their childhood held secrets mine didn’t. Darkness that no child should know. And yet we wore the same meeting clothes, carried the same book bags, knocked on the same doors with the same practiced smiles.</p>

<p>Their sister disappeared one day. No explanation. No goodbye. Just gone, sent to live with grandparents while the family continued their charade of righteousness. The brothers wondered, but children in the “truth” learn early not to ask questions that might have uncomfortable answers.</p>

<p>It would be ten years before they learned why she vanished. Ten years of their father sitting in the Kingdom Hall. Ten years of their mother’s silence. Ten years of pretending everything was fine while a child’s life had been shattered beyond repair.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“My father raped a child. Yet I am the monstrous black sheep of the family, because I left.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>There it is. The truth that turns everything upside down. In the careful mathematics of high-control religion, leaving the faith is the unforgivable sin. Everything else can be overlooked, hidden, forgiven. But apostasy? That’s the only crime that matters.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-shepherd-who-hunted">The Shepherd Who Hunted</h2>

<p>At fifteen, they made the mistake of being caught with a Stephen King novel. In the congregation’s eyes, this made them “bad association”: spiritually dangerous, in need of stronger guidance. The elders had a solution: spend time with Larry, a ministerial servant. A spiritual mentor. Someone to set them on the right path.</p>

<p>I wonder sometimes about the delicate trust of children. How we hand it over to those who wear the right clothes, say the right words, carry the right title. Larry wore all of those things.</p>

<p>They woke one night to find his hands where they shouldn’t be. A child, frozen in the dark, trying to make sense of why God’s servant was doing this. They hid in the bathroom until morning light made it safe to call for rescue. But they never said why they stopped visiting Larry. Who would believe the “bad association” kid over a respected ministerial servant?</p>

<p>A year later, at a congregation gathering (one of those wholesome get-togethers with water gun fights and potluck dishes), Larry found them alone in a bathroom. Tried again. This time, they fought. Hit him with a water gun and ran.</p>

<p>Such a small weapon against such a large betrayal. But they fought.</p>

<p>When they finally found the courage to tell their parents years later, nothing changed. The story was received and filed away. They remained the problem. The apostate. The one who abandoned Jehovah.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-sister-who-carried-too-much">The Sister Who Carried Too Much</h2>

<p>When they escaped at twenty-one, their first act of freedom was to find their sister. After a decade of silence, they needed to know she had survived.</p>

<p>She had, but barely.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“She was killing herself with drugs and alcohol just to cope. No matter what I tried I could not stop her downward spiral, she killed herself about 13 years ago.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Thirteen years, and the wound still bleeds through their words. How could it not? Their sister was sacrificed to protect an image. Sent away like a shameful secret instead of a child who needed justice, needed healing, needed someone to believe her.</p>

<p>When the pain finally became unbearable, she chose the only door she could find. And their parents, those guardians of righteousness, couldn’t even honor her in death. Attending an apostate’s funeral might displease Jehovah. Even if that apostate was your daughter. Even if her life ended because no one protected her when it mattered.</p>

<p>The same absence marked their grandparents’ funerals. Death after death, and the empty chairs where family should have been standing. All for an organization that protected the abuser and exiled the abused.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-price-of-asking-why">The Price of Asking Why</h2>

<p>After losing everything—family, friends, community, God himself—what remains? For them, it became a desperate negotiation with the universe:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I figured the universe, or ‘god’ owed me some answers. I had literally, nothing else to lose.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>They dove deep into the searching. Read the Bible twelve times, looking for truth between the lines they’d been taught. Studied the origins of those ancient stories. Traced the fingerprints of older gods on newer scriptures. They weren’t just leaving a religion. They were archaeologists excavating their own buried truth from under decades of carefully constructed lies.</p>

<p>They tried to build something normal from the rubble. Got a good job with AT&amp;T. Moved to Omaha. Wore business clothes instead of meeting clothes. Focused on the material world they’d been taught to despise.</p>

<p>For a while, it almost worked.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="when-the-universe-answers">When the Universe Answers</h2>

<p>Near Thanksgiving 2007, something happened that would push them even further into isolation. They describe beings coming through their apartment wall like ghosts. An experience so far outside acceptable reality that sharing it became another kind of exile.</p>

<p>I won’t pretend to understand what happened that night. What matters is that someone who had already lost everything to their search for truth was given an experience that made that truth even harder to share. Another layer of separation. Another reason to stay quiet.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Once the universe gives you glasses, and you put them on, you can never take them off, and you cannot force anyone else to look through them.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>After begging the universe for truth, they received something that made them even more alone. There’s a terrible poetry in that: to survive religious trauma only to be handed a reality that isolates you further. To escape one unbelievable truth only to encounter another.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-geography-of-loneliness">The Geography of Loneliness</h2>

<p>They live alone now. Carry all of this packed away as carefully as they can manage. Their parents are aging, and they wrestle with whether to attend the funerals of people who wouldn’t attend their sister’s. Who wouldn’t attend theirs.</p>

<p>But here’s what takes my breath away: After everything—the abuse that should have destroyed them, the betrayals that should have made them bitter, the losses that should have ended them, the experiences that pushed them beyond what most can accept—they answered my call for stories.</p>

<p>They saw my invitation and thought: <em>Yes. I’ll trust one more time. I’ll speak one more truth. I’ll reach across this vast loneliness and see if anyone reaches back.</em></p>

<p>That’s not just survival. That’s the most profound kind of courage I know.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="why-every-word-matters">Why Every Word Matters</h2>

<p>In high-control religions, the architecture of silence is carefully built. Children learn which truths are speakable and which must be swallowed. Victims discover that their pain matters less than the congregation’s reputation. Those who finally speak face exile as their reward for honesty.</p>

<p>This person’s journey, from childhood in “the truth” to searching for truth among the stars, maps the territory so many of us travel after religious trauma. When the foundation cracks, when everything you believed becomes suspect, sometimes you have to be willing to look everywhere for what’s real. Even if that search takes you places others can’t follow.</p>

<hr />

<p>To the person who shared this story: Thank you.</p>

<p>Your truth matters. Every word of it. Even the parts others might not believe.</p>

<p>Your sister mattered. Your pain matters. Your search for truth matters.</p>

<p>And you matter. Not as an apostate. Not as a cautionary tale. But as a human being who deserved protection, love, and truth from the very beginning.</p>

<p>Thank you for answering my call. Thank you for trusting me with your broken bird of a story. I’m holding it carefully, I promise.</p>

<hr />

<div class="author-note">
<p><strong>From Mileena:</strong> This story came to me after I put out a call asking people to share their experiences, promising that their voices would be heard and their stories would matter. I'm grateful this person trusted me with something so profound and painful.</p>

<p>If you're an ex-JW or religious trauma survivor with a story to share, I'm here to listen. Sometimes the greatest healing comes from simply being heard. <a href="/contact/">Reach out anytime</a>.</p>

<p>And to those still trapped: The world outside is frightening, yes. You'll lose people you love. But there's truth out here. Real, complicated, difficult truth. And it's worth everything you'll sacrifice to find it.</p>

<p>You are not alone in this. Even when it feels like you are. Even when the truth makes you strange. Even when the universe shows you things others won't believe. You are not alone.</p>
</div>

<hr />

<h2 id="video-version">Video Version</h2>

<div class="video-container">
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/z3upFeetDT0?si=JW6zusTUBMnKQYh9" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<style>
.video-notice-box {
    background: linear-gradient(135deg, rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.15), rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.08));
    border: 1px solid #8a9fff;
    border-radius: 10px;
    padding: 15px 20px;
    margin-bottom: 20px;
    font-size: 0.95em;
    color: #b8c5ff;
    text-align: center;
}

.content-warning-box {
    background: rgba(255, 100, 100, 0.1);
    border: 1px solid #ff6464;
    border-radius: 10px;
    padding: 20px;
    margin-bottom: 40px;
    font-size: 0.95em;
    color: #ffaaaa;
}

.video-container {
    position: relative;
    padding-bottom: 56.25%; /* 16:9 aspect ratio */
    height: 0;
    overflow: hidden;
    max-width: 100%;
    background: #000;
    border-radius: 10px;
    margin: 30px 0;
}

.video-container iframe {
    position: absolute;
    top: 0;
    left: 0;
    width: 100%;
    height: 100%;
    border-radius: 10px;
}

.author-note {
    background: linear-gradient(135deg, rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.1), rgba(138, 159, 255, 0.05));
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    border-radius: 0 15px 15px 0;
    padding: 30px;
    margin: 60px 0 40px 0;
    font-style: italic;
}

.author-note p {
    margin-bottom: 15px;
    line-height: 1.8;
}

.author-note p:last-child {
    margin-bottom: 0;
}

blockquote {
    background: rgba(40, 40, 50, 0.5);
    border-left: 4px solid #8a9fff;
    padding: 20px 30px;
    margin: 30px 0;
    font-style: italic;
    color: #ddd;
    border-radius: 0 10px 10px 0;
}

h2 {
    color: #f0f0f0;
    font-weight: 300;
    font-size: 2em;
    margin-top: 60px;
    margin-bottom: 30px;
    letter-spacing: 1px;
}

hr {
    border: none;
    height: 1px;
    background: linear-gradient(to right, transparent, #8a9fff, transparent);
    margin: 60px 0;
}
</style>]]></content><author><name>Mileena Rayne</name></author><category term="Community Stories" /><category term="jehovahs-witness" /><category term="religious-trauma" /><category term="sexual-abuse" /><category term="family-betrayal" /><category term="truth-seeking" /><category term="survivor-stories" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When I asked for ex-JW stories, one person trusted me with their journey through family sexual abuse, religious betrayal, devastating loss, and a desperate search for truth that led beyond this world.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/when-everything-you-knew-was-a-lie.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/when-everything-you-knew-was-a-lie.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">From Jehovah’s Witness to Nurse to Author: Turning Religious Trauma Into Storytelling</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/21/from-jehovahs-witness-to-nurse-to-author/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Jehovah’s Witness to Nurse to Author: Turning Religious Trauma Into Storytelling" /><published>2025-06-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-06-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/21/from-jehovahs-witness-to-nurse-to-author</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/21/from-jehovahs-witness-to-nurse-to-author/"><![CDATA[<p>When people hear “Jehovah’s Witness,” they usually think of the well-dressed, polite people knocking on doors on a quiet weekend morning. But for those of us who grew up inside it, there’s a lot more beneath that polished surface. What people see is a clean exterior, but the depth of control, fear, and isolation within that lifestyle runs deep.</p>

<p>I was a Jehovah’s Witness for 18 years. My best friend growing up was the daughter of a prominent elder, which meant I was always close to what was considered the “right” way of doing things. I was never baptized, but that didn’t shield me from the same expectations. In the eyes of my community, I “knew better,” so I was judged—and punished—accordingly.</p>

<p>The consequences of that judgment shaped every aspect of my childhood. It wasn’t just about missing out on birthday cupcakes at school. It meant I wasn’t allowed to have friends outside the religion, which was incredibly isolating. We were expected to preach to classmates, often putting us in uncomfortable, confrontational situations. I remember being mocked, getting into arguments with both students and teachers, and feeling ashamed for just existing differently. We were children, but we were taught to be soldiers of faith—taught we should be ready to die for our beliefs.</p>

<h2 id="practicing-for-death">Practicing for Death</h2>

<p>We practiced skits about being handed a slip of paper and told that signing it would save our lives if we renounced our faith. The message? Don’t sign. Die faithful. And that kind of conditioning didn’t stop there. We were told never to accept blood transfusions, even if it meant death. We were constantly reminded that Armageddon could come at any time, and we were shown vivid illustrations of death, destruction—crows pecking the eyes from corpses we were supposedly going to help clean up after God’s wrath.</p>

<p>But the trauma that stuck with me most was being told I would never grow old. That the End would come first. That I would live in a paradise on Earth, in perfect health, forever young. Coming to terms with the fact that I will age and will die has been one of the hardest parts of my healing. The anxiety it causes is deep. I didn’t grow up knowing death was a part of life—I grew up thinking death was for those who didn’t believe.</p>

<h2 id="finding-life-in-healthcare">Finding Life in Healthcare</h2>

<p>Maybe it was inevitable that someone so afraid of death would end up working so closely with it. I started working in healthcare at 17—first as a CNA, later in psychiatric and pharmaceutical research, and eventually as a registered nurse. Working in long-term care helped me see aging as something natural. But even now, after pronouncing deaths as an RN, I still struggle to accept the reality of mortality. It’s a truth I was never prepared to face.</p>

<p>Healthcare taught me something the religion never could: how to witness suffering without having all the answers. How to sit with people’s pain without needing to explain it away or promise it would all make sense someday. Sometimes healing isn’t about fixing—it’s about being present.</p>

<h2 id="when-anger-fades-into-understanding">When Anger Fades Into Understanding</h2>

<p>But even as I was learning to help others process their pain, I was still carrying my own. After leaving the Jehovah’s Witnesses, I felt a strong need to help others, especially those also trying to escape or make sense of their past. I joined a Facebook group for ex-Witnesses and those questioning the religion. But being there started to retraumatize me. The wounds people carried were raw. Their stories brought back my own pain. I reached a point where my blinding anger started to fade, and I began to see my trauma in a more nuanced light.</p>

<p>I no longer want to “burn down Kingdom Halls.” I’ve let go of the belief that every Jehovah’s Witness is evil. Many are genuinely kind people who truly believe they are doing what’s right. It took me years to understand that and to be okay with it.</p>

<h2 id="writing-my-way-to-truth">Writing My Way to Truth</h2>

<p>That shift is part of what led me to write <em>The Chosen</em>, the second book in my series. I started writing it after publishing <em>The Silence</em>. The world in my story had been plunged into darkness, and I thought—what comes after a collapse like that? Religion. In real life, people often turn to faith during chaos, and I wanted to explore how easily people fall into high-control belief systems after trauma.</p>

<p>In <em>The Chosen</em>, the group called Zenith’s Chosen is directly inspired by Jehovah’s Witnesses. Mira Roehart, my protagonist, carries many of my thoughts and feelings. Her friend, Katalina (Kat), is modeled after my childhood best friend. I made Kat a deeply zealous character—someone lovable but indoctrinated—because that’s how my friend was. She wasn’t cruel, just fully immersed in her beliefs. I want readers to feel the tension of that dynamic. How someone can hurt you without meaning to, and how love can still exist within painful memories.</p>

<p>Chapter 24—Thank You for the Privilege of Losing Everything—dives into the emotional aftermath of leaving a high-control group. It explores how people, in their pain, can become something they once hated. The quotes from that chapter still hit me:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You lie and you say Zenith’ll give them a home, a family, a future—but one wrong step, one whispered doubt, one godsdamn mistake… Poof. Gone. Just like that. How is that justice?”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You tear apart families! You condemn us to die alone and afraid, cast out like vermin, like we ain’t even human!”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Do you have ANY IDEA what it’s like? To have your entire life—your family, your friends—ripped away like you never mattered?”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You forsake us. You forget we ever existed. And then you act like we should thank you! Thank you for the privilege of losing everything.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Every one of those lines came from a place of lived experience. That bitterness, that raw anger—I lived it. But in my story, Mira prevents a character from killing a member of Zenith’s Chosen, despite once feeling the same rage. That moment is about healing. It shows how we can go from cheering on vengeance to choosing mercy. That level of healing doesn’t feel possible when your wounds are fresh—but I wanted to show that it can happen.</p>

<h2 id="from-trauma-to-medicine">From Trauma to Medicine</h2>

<p>The parallel between my nursing work and my writing became clearer as I worked on this book. My hope is that <em>The Chosen</em> helps people who’ve left Jehovah’s Witnesses—or anyone who’s struggled with religious control—see themselves in the story. See how easy it is to fall into these systems. See that there’s a way out. And most importantly, see that recovery is possible.</p>

<p>Both nursing and writing have taught me the same thing: sometimes the most powerful medicine comes from simply being witnessed. From having someone say, “I see your pain, and it matters.”</p>

<p>This book is still a work in progress, but every chapter I write feels like another step toward turning trauma into something that heals instead of harms. Not just for me, but for anyone who recognizes their own story in Mira’s journey.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>If you’ve left a high-control religious group or are considering it, know that you’re not alone. <a href="/chapters/the-chosen/chapter-01/">Read Chapter 1 of The Chosen</a> to see Mira’s world before everything changes—and follow her journey as she navigates the seductive promises of those who claim to offer light.</em></p>

<p><em>You can also read more about <a href="/writing/">my current writing projects</a> and how personal experience shapes every story I tell.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Mileena Rayne</name></author><category term="Diary Entry" /><category term="jehovahs-witness" /><category term="religious-trauma" /><category term="nursing" /><category term="healthcare" /><category term="the-chosen" /><category term="writing-journey" /><category term="healing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How eighteen years in a high-control religious group shaped my path from healthcare to dark fantasy writing. The journey from trauma to truth-telling through fiction.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/mileena-rayne-author.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/mileena-rayne-author.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rose in the Snow - New Folk Song About Overcoming Stalkers and Doubters</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/18/the-story-behind-rose-in-the-snow/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rose in the Snow - New Folk Song About Overcoming Stalkers and Doubters" /><published>2025-06-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-06-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/18/the-story-behind-rose-in-the-snow</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/18/the-story-behind-rose-in-the-snow/"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Rose in the Snow”</em> is a song about being watched, doubted, and silently resented—yet choosing to bloom anyway.</p>

<p>This one came from a place I don’t often speak about. It’s about the strange ache of knowing people who never supported you are still watching you. Not to cheer you on, but to quietly hope you’ll fall. It’s about the kind of presence that hides behind silence—people who never say a word but click through everything you post. Who linger. Who lurk. Who know your highs and lows better than some of your family. And it’s about the ones who tried to bury you with doubt, with judgment, with absence—and are still shocked when you rise.</p>

<h2 id="more-than-just-survival">More Than Just Survival</h2>

<p>But <em>Rose in the Snow</em> isn’t just a song about being stalked or underestimated. It’s a song about defiance. About surviving what was meant to break you. About growing in places that were never meant to nurture you. It’s about refusing to shrink, even when the people around you are more comfortable with your silence.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“They tried to bury all that I could be, But the frost couldn’t tame the flame in me.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>That line became the heartbeat of this song. It’s the answer to every person who thought I would stay buried under their projections. Every person who pretended not to care, while obsessively tracking everything I did. Every person who said nothing while wishing for failure behind a screen.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“You won’t say a word, but you want the tea— Sippin’ my pain like it’s VIP.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="a-message-of-defiance">A Message of Defiance</h2>

<p>This is for anyone who’s ever felt quietly hated, quietly doubted, quietly watched. This is for the survivors, the creators, the ones who grew without permission. This is for the ones who chose to bloom through the frost, with no apology.</p>

<p>I am that rose. Still blooming. Still here.</p>

<p>And I’m not going anywhere.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Experience the full song with its visualizer and find all my music on my <a href="/music/">Music page</a>.</strong></p>

<p><em>Have you ever felt like you were being quietly watched or underestimated? This song is for you. Sometimes the most powerful thing we can do is simply refuse to stop growing.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Mileena Rayne</name></author><category term="Music" /><category term="rose-in-the-snow" /><category term="folk-music" /><category term="stalking" /><category term="survival" /><category term="defiance" /><category term="new-song" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The story behind my latest folk song Rose in the Snow - about being stalked, underestimated, and quietly resented, yet choosing to bloom anyway. A defiant anthem for survivors.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/mileena-rayne-author.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/mileena-rayne-author.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Blood of the Wild Gods Series - Dark Fantasy About Cults and Trauma</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/17/current-works-in-progress/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blood of the Wild Gods Series - Dark Fantasy About Cults and Trauma" /><published>2025-06-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-06-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/17/current-works-in-progress</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/17/current-works-in-progress/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m currently working on two very different projects. The first is <em>The Chosen</em>, the sequel to my debut novel <em>The Silence</em> in my <em>Blood of the Wild Gods</em> series. It takes place five years after the events of the first book. The realm is fractured. People are desperate for something to believe in—some steady ground after so many waves have crashed through their lives. Then a man appears from the eastern islands, bringing promises of light and order. In a time of chaos, people cling to it. And slowly, my main character’s quiet coastal town begins to change.</p>

<p>This book dives into the psychology of cults—how easy it is to fall into them, how isolating it can be once you’re inside, and how damaging blind certainty can become. I based the group known as Zenith’s Chosen on the high-control religious environment I was raised in from birth until I finally left at eighteen. In many ways, this story mirrors my own. I didn’t realize it at first, but writing this book became a way of working through the trauma I carried from that time.</p>

<p>I’ve always wanted to do something meaningful for others who’ve left controlling religious groups—or who are still trapped in them and thinking about leaving. I didn’t know how to help practically, but this book became my answer. It’s my offering. My way of saying: I see you. You’re not alone. I hope it does that justice.</p>

<p>My second project started as a side escape—something lighthearted to give me a break from the emotional intensity of <em>The Chosen</em>—but it quickly grew into a passion project of its own. It’s called <em>The Lost Histories</em>, and it’s narrated by Tanneus G’Raja, a scholar from the Hollow Spire who guides the reader through the forgotten myths and legends of this world. You’re discovering these stories right alongside him, and his voice adds a layer of introspection I’ve never seen done quite like this before. He prepares you for what’s coming, then gently helps you process what you’ve just read—not by telling you what to think, but by giving you space to think more deeply.</p>

<p>Originally, I just wanted to flesh out the backstories of the gods so I could reference them in the main series. But the project became so much more than that. It built a richer, more interconnected world. Some characters even cross over between stories. Some truths in this book reshape how you see events in <em>The Chosen</em>. I love those “Oh wait…!” moments as a reader, and I’ve tried to create that same experience here.</p>

<p>What I’m most proud of, though, is how these stories explore the deeper layers of what it means to be human. They touch on themes like how history is rewritten by those in power, how belief systems can evolve or be manipulated, and how obsession—like stalking—can shatter lives in tragic and disturbing ways. They’re heavy topics, but I believe they’re worth facing.</p>

<p>At the heart of everything I write is a desire to connect—not to provide escape, but to create space for reflection. I don’t flinch away from hard truths. I know that means my work won’t be for everyone. I know it’ll make some people uncomfortable or even upset. But that’s the point. These subjects are uncomfortable to live through, so I believe they should be uncomfortable to read about too. Not to glorify them, but to expose them for what they are.</p>

<p>My goal is never to romanticize trauma. It’s to be honest about it. To help people who’ve never lived it understand how devastating it is—and to offer recognition and maybe even healing to those who have.</p>

<p>I know this kind of writing isn’t likely to make me famous. But that’s not why I write. I write to tell the truth, even when it hurts. Especially when it hurts.</p>

<p><a href="/writing/">Read more about both projects and sample chapters on my Writing page →</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Mileena Rayne</name></author><category term="Writing" /><category term="dark-fantasy" /><category term="blood-of-wild-gods" /><category term="cults" /><category term="religious-trauma" /><category term="fantasy-novels" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Inside look at my dark fantasy novels The Chosen and Lost Histories. Stories exploring cult psychology, religious trauma, and the deeper layers of human nature.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/EbookPic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/EbookPic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to My Little Refuge - Starting Over After Homelessness</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/16/welcome-to-my-little-refuge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to My Little Refuge - Starting Over After Homelessness" /><published>2025-06-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-06-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/16/welcome-to-my-little-refuge</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/diary/2025/06/16/welcome-to-my-little-refuge/"><![CDATA[<p>Here it is. My website. A place I’ve finally decided to create so I can share my creative work and unfiltered thoughts—and maybe spare my friends and family a little bit on social media.</p>

<p>This all came about after a really difficult chapter in my life. I recently experienced homelessness. And when I made it through that and finally found stable housing, I shared a post on social media to process everything I’d gone through. I needed to say it out loud. To reflect, to release it. A lot of people responded with compassion and said it resonated with them—but some took it the wrong way. That part really hurt.</p>

<p>Something I was traumatized by was turned around and thrown back at me, like it was just a choice I made. I don’t think it was said with malice, but it still stung. It made me realize something: <strong>I need my own space.</strong> A place where I can speak freely and reach the people who actually want to hear what I have to say—not just react to it. A space for people who are drawn to my music, my writing, my way of seeing the world.</p>

<h2 id="finding-my-voice">Finding My Voice</h2>

<p>Over time, I’ve come a long way in how I express myself. I’ve learned how to communicate what’s on my mind, even the hard stuff. I’ve realized I have a lot to say—and it’s worth saying. I’ve lived through things that gave me perspective and insight, and I think that matters.</p>

<p>I’ve always been someone who’s willing to say the things most people don’t dare to. It’s both a blessing and a curse. But I believe in the power of honesty—the raw, unfiltered kind. The kind that exposes not just the hard and ugly parts of life, but the beautiful, unrestrained parts too.</p>

<h2 id="my-little-refuge">My Little Refuge</h2>

<p>So this is my space. My little refuge. And maybe, if you’ve been needing something like this, it can be yours too.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Sometimes we need to create our own corners of the world where our truth can breathe freely.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here, I’ll share the music that pours out of me at 3 AM. The stories that demand to be told. The thoughts that feel too big for small talk but too important to keep silent. The messy, beautiful, complicated reality of being human in a world that often prefers its truth sanitized and its emotions at a comfortable distance.</p>

<p>If you’re here, thank you for choosing to listen. Thank you for being someone who isn’t afraid of depth, who doesn’t need me to dim my light to make you comfortable in your darkness.</p>

<p>Welcome to my little refuge. Make yourself at home.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>This space is for anyone who’s ever felt too much, loved too hard, or seen too clearly in a world that prefers the surface. You belong here.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Mileena Rayne</name></author><category term="Diary Entry" /><category term="homelessness" /><category term="recovery" /><category term="authenticity" /><category term="truth-telling" /><category term="creative-writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My journey from homelessness to finding my voice. Why I created this space for authentic creative work and unfiltered thoughts about trauma, recovery, and truth-telling.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/mileena-rayne-author.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/mileena-rayne-author.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>